<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exercise for a Christian familie; contayning a short sum of certayne poyntes of Christian religion, with certaine godly prayers, psalmes, &amp; thanksgiuings, both before and after meales. Very necessary to be vsed in euery Christian familie. / By R.M..</title>
            <author>R. M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17145.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94072</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">54532414</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 54532414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00400)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2139:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exercise for a Christian familie; contayning a short sum of certayne poyntes of Christian religion, with certaine godly prayers, psalmes, &amp; thanksgiuings, both before and after meales. Very necessary to be vsed in euery Christian familie. / By R.M..</title>
                  <author>R. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 238 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegraue.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette (royal arms); head-pieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-K¹².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Cardiff Central Library (Wales).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180838:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180838:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180838:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180838:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180838:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180838:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An exerciſe for a Chriſtian FAMILIE; <hi>Contayning a ſhort ſum</hi> of certayne poyntes of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, with certaine godly</hi> Prayers, pſalmes, &amp; than<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuings, both before and after meales.</p>
            <p>¶ Very neceſſary to be vſed in euery Christian Familie. <hi>By R. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON ¶ Printed by Robert Walde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue. 1585.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180838:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180838:4"/>
            <head>¶ A short SVMME OF THE cheefe groundes of <hi>chriſtian religion, ſet down in fiue ſpeciall points.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>anctify the lord God in your hearts,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.15.</note> &amp; be ready alwayes to giue an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to euery one that asketh you a reaſon of your fayth, &amp; that with meekeneſſe and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:180838:5"/>
            <p>Keepe the true patern of the wholſome words which thou haſte heard of me in faith and loue,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.13.</note> which is, Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>I Beleeue and confeſſe firſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.10.</note> that there is * one God onelye, who * is a ſpirituall nature,<note place="margin">Ioh. 45.5</note> without any bodily or viſible ſharpe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.24 1. Tim. 6 16. Exo. 34.6 Pſa. 95.4</note> * of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite power, wiſedome, * goodneſſe and glory, creator and gouernour of heauen and earth, &amp; that this one god, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct into * three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the father,<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.7</note> the ſon, and the holy ghoſt.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:180838:5"/>
            <p>Secondly, that the ſame God did in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning * make mankinde in an excellent ſtate of all perfection &amp; happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26</note> euen according to his owne * holineſſe &amp; righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Eph 4.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that we fell afterwards through the diſobedience of Adam, into a curſed kind of al miſery,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12</note> euen * into the wrath of God and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal damnation of body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from this miſery, is fully wrought by * Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus<note place="margin">Actes. 4.12.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180838:6"/>Chriſt onely, both God &amp; man, who hath * ſuffered all the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our ſinns,<note place="margin">Rom. 13 4</note> that we might not bee dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for them,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1 7 1. Pet. 2 24.</note> * &amp; hath perfectly kept the * ten commaundements for vs, which we could not do, to bring vs again to the * loue of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.19
21</note> and to eternal life.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, that they onely are partakers of Ieſus Chriſte and * this great worke of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Math. 7.7</note> which do earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully praye for the grace of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly * Spirite,<note place="margin">Rom. 10 11</note> that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180838:6"/>the * preaching of the Worde,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.36.</note> there maye bee wroughte in their heartes a * ſtedfaſt fayth,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.18 21.</note> to be ſaued by his ſufferings and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe onely, and that their fayth may be ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed and iuſtyfied by continuall repentance, and a Godly life, that is,<note place="margin">Deu. 12
12.</note> by * ſhunning thoſe thinges which hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth, and dooing thoſe thinges which he commaundeth.</p>
            <p>This is lyfe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.3.</note> to knowe thee to bee the onelye true God, and him whome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180838:7"/>thou haſte ſente, Ieſus Chriſte.<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ieſus ſayd, take heede and beware of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the phariſees &amp; ſaduces,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.6 12.</note> which is their doctrine.</p>
            <p>Caſt away prophane and old wiues fables,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.7</note> &amp; exerciſe thy ſelfe vnto godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>I will pray vnto God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.16.</note> and the Lord ſhall ſaue mee, euening and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and at noone day will I pray, and he will heare my voyce.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:180838:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Prayers for the morning,</hi> neceſſary to be vſed of all houſholders in their families.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>MATH. 26.41.</bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>VVatch and pray, leaſt ye enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O moſte mighty God our heauenly and mercifull father, we moſt wretched ſinners, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye confeſſe vnto thy maieſty, that all good thinges wee haue, doe come from thy onelye mercy, that we are moſt vnworthy of them, and yet altogether vnable heartily to pray for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180838:8"/>continuaunce thereof, yet ſeeing thy dear ſon Ieſus Chriſte, hathe commaunded vs in his name, to pray, and that with aſſurance to ſpeed and to be heard: wee beſeeche thee for his ſake, to prepare oure heartes by thy holye ſpirite, to put oute of our mindes all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye thinges and vayne fantaſies, and to ſtir vs vp earneſtly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what greate neede wee haue of thy continuall help both in our ſoules and bodies. O Lord we haue through our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180838:8"/>ſinns, deſerued thy wrath, and eternall damnation of body &amp; ſoul, yet by the vertue of the great ſufferinges of Ieſus Chriſt, and the ſhedding of his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud, forgiue and waſh away al our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: wee are vnworthy of thy fauour, either in this life or in the life to come, yet thorough his holines, receiue vs vnto mercy, &amp; make vs heirs of thy bleſſed kingdom and ſo increaſe in oure hearts euery day, vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentaunce for our former wickednes,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180838:9"/>in that we haue neither worſhipped thy maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, nor liued towardes others, accordinge to thy worde. Strengthen our faith (O Lord) in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of our ſinnes, and for thy tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſake, powre into our hearts the grace of thy holy ſpirite, which may ſtirre vp in vs a more hearty loue vnto thee and thy bleſſed worde, that by it we may learn to worſhip thee aright, and to liue faithfullye, &amp; truelye towardes all men in our callings, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180838:9"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually againſt all ſinne, chiefly in our ſelues, and then alſo in others, ſo that whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it ſhall pleaſe thee to call any of vs out of this ſhort &amp; ſinfull life, we may willingly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vp our ſoules into thy bleſſed kingdome, and may come with ioy (as louing children) to thee our heauenly and merciful Father. O lord make vs thankful for all thy corrections, giuing vs grace by them to fear thee more carefully, &amp; to ſorow for our ſinnes more heartily. Make vs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180838:10"/>alſo thankfull for all thy benefites, namely, for the ſweete ſleepe and quiet reſt, wherby thou haſte this nighte refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed vs, wee beſeeche thee now in like manner (O gratious God) for Chriſts ſake, to receiue vs this day into thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed keeping, preſerue vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al perils &amp; dangers, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinn, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked cares of this life, and the vaine deſires of the fleſh, ſhinning into our hearts by the grace of thy holy ſpirit, and the true knowledge of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the true light
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180838:10"/>of the worlde, that wee may guid al ourthoghts words, &amp; deeds, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame, and walk painfully and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our callings, to the glorye of thy bleſſed name, the good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of al others, and the great aſſuraunce of our own ſaluation, through thy deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſte our onely ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, in whoſe name we pary for theſe, and al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces, as hee hath taught vs ſaying, Our father &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:180838:11"/>
               <head>Another Prayer for the Morning.</head>
               <p>ALmighty God, and moſte mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Dan. 9</note> we do not * preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our ſelues heere before thy maieſty, truſting in oure owne merites or worthineſſe, but in thy manifolde mercies, which haſt promiſed to heare our prayers and * graunt oure requeſts,<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.</note> which we ſhall make to thee in the name of thy beloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, who hath alſo commanded
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180838:11"/>vs to aſse<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble our ſelues together in his * name,<note place="margin">Math.
18.</note> with full aſſurance that he will not onely bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, but alſo be our mediator, &amp; * aduocate towardes thy maieſtie,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> that we may obtain * all things which ſhall ſeem expedient to thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will for our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.</note> Therefore wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full father, to turne thy louing countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs,<note place="margin">Pſal.
32.</note> and * impute not vnto vs our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde ſins &amp; offences, whereby wee iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thy wrath &amp; ſharp
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180838:12"/>puniſhment: but rather receiue vs to thy mercy for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, accepting his death and paſſion as a iuſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for all our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in whom only thou art pleaſed, &amp; through whome thou canſt not bee offended with vs. And ſeeing that of thy great mercies wee haue quietli paſſed this night grant, o heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, that wee may beſtowe this day wholly in thy ſeruice, ſo that all oure thoughtes, wordes and deeds may redound to the glory of thy name,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180838:12"/>and good example to al men: who ſeeing our good works, may glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy thee our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And foraſmuch as of thy mere fauour and loue thou haſt not only created vs to thine own ſimilitude &amp; likeneſſe, but alſo haſte choſen vs to bee heires with thy dear ſonne Ieſus Chriſt of that immortall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which thou prepa redſt for vs before the begining of the world, wee beſeech thee to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſ our faith &amp; know ledge, &amp; to lighten our heartes with thine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180838:13"/>ſpirit, that we may in the meane time liue in godly conuerſation &amp; integrity of life, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that * idolaters,<note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> adul terers, couetous men, contentious perſonnes, drunkardes, gluttons &amp; ſuch like, ſhall not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the kingdome of God.</p>
               <p>And becauſe thou haſte commaunded vs to pray one for another we doe not onely make requeſt, O Lord, for our ſelues, and them that thou haſt already called to thee true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of thine heauenly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180838:13"/>will, but for all people &amp; * natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the world,<note place="margin">Actes.
10. 1. tim. 2.</note> who as they knowe by thy wonderful workes, that thou art God ouer all, ſo they may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by thine holie ſpirite, to beleue in thee their onely ſauiour and Redeemer. But foras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they can not beleeue except they * hear,<note place="margin">Rom.
10.</note> nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not hear but by preaching, and none can preach except they be ſent, therfore, O lord raiſe vp faythfull diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buters of thy miſteries, who ſetting aparte all worldly reſpectes, may
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:180838:14"/>both in their life and doctrine only ſeeke thy glory. Contrarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde * Sathan,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt with all hirelings and papiſtes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt already caſt of into a reprobate ſenſe, that they may not by ſects, ſchiſmes, hereſies and errours diſquiet thy lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle flocke. And becauſe, O Lorde, wee be fallen into the latter dayes,<note place="margin">2. tim. 3.</note> and daungerous times wherin ignorance hath gotten the vpper hand, and Satan with his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters ſeeke by all meanes to quench the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:180838:14"/>light of thy Goſpell, we beſeeche thee to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy cauſe againſt thoſe * rauenous wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,<note place="margin">Mat. 7</note> and ſtrengthen all thy ſeruauntes, whome they keepe in priſon &amp; bondage. Let not thy long ſuffering bee an occaſion eyther to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their tyranny, or to diſcourage thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, neyther yet let oure ſinnes and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe bee an hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deraunce to thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes, but with ſpeede, O Lord, conſider the greate myſeries, and afflictions of thy poore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:180838:15"/>Church, which in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places by the rage of enimies is greeuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tormented: and this we confeſſe, O Lord, to come moſte iuſtlye for our ſinnes which (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thy mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold benefites, whereby thou doeſt dayly allure vs to loue thee: and thy ſharp thretnings, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we haue occaſion to feare thee, and ſpeedily to repent) yet continue in our owne wickednes and feel not our hearts ſo touched with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of our ſinnes as we ought to do. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:180838:15"/>O Lorde, create in vs newe heartes, that with feruent minds we may bewaile our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde ſinnes, &amp; earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent vs for our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wickedneſſe and vngodly behauiour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes thee: and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as wee can not of oure ſelues purchaſe thy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, yet wee humblye beſeeche thee for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, to ſhewe thy mercies vppon vs, and receiue vs again to thy fauour. Graunt vs, deare father, theſe oure requeſtes, and all other thinges neceſſary for vs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180838:16"/>and thy whole Church according to thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: in whoſe name we beſeech thee, as hee hath taught vs, ſaying, Our Father which art in heauen, hallowed be thy name. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A GODLY PRAIER</hi> to be ſayde at all times.</head>
               <p>HOnour and prayſe bee giuen to thee, O Lord God almighty, moſte deare Father of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:180838:16"/>heauen, for all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies &amp; louing kindneſſe ſhewed vnto vs, in that it hath pleſed thy gratious goodneſſe and freely of thine own accord, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect &amp; chuſe vs to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the begining of the world: &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual thanks be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thee for creating vs after thine own image, for redeeming vs with the precious bloude of thy deare ſonne, when we were vtterlye loſte, for ſanctifying vs with thine holye Spirite in the Reuelation and knowledge of thyne
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:180838:17"/>holy word, for helping and ſuccouring vs in all our needes and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for ſauing vs from all daungers of bodye and ſoule, for comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs ſo fatherly in all our tribulations &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, for ſparing vs ſo long, and giuing vs ſo large a time of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. Theſe benefits, O moſt merciful father, like as wee knowledge to haue receiued them of thine onely good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, euen ſo wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, for thy dear ſon Ieſus Chriſtes ſake to grant vs alwais thine
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:180838:17"/>holy ſpirit, whereby we may continually growe in thankfulnes towards thee, to bee led into all truethe, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in all oure aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. O Lord, ſtrengthen our faith: kindle it more in feruentnes and loue towardes thee and our neighbors for thy ſake. Suffer vs not, moſt dear Father, to receiue thy word any more in vain, but graunt vs alwayes the aſſiſtaunce of thy grace and holy ſpirite, that in heart, word, and deede we may ſanctify and doe worſhip to thy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180838:18"/>name, helpe to amplify and increaſe thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that whatſoeuer thou ſendeſt, we maye be hartely well content with thy good pleaſure and wil. Let vs not lack the thing, o father, with out the which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerue thee, but bleſſ thou ſo all the workes of our handes, that we may haue ſufficient, and not to bee chargeable, but rather helpfull vnto others. Be mercifull, O Lorde, to our offences: and ſeeing our debt is great, which thou haſte forgiuen vs in Ieſus
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:180838:18"/>Chriſt, make vs to loue thee and our neighbors ſo much the more. Be thou oure Father, oure captaine and defender, in all tentations: holde thou vs by thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand, that we maye bee deliuered from all inconueniences, &amp; end our liues in the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; honor of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name through Ieſus chriſt our Lord, &amp; only Sauioure, ſo be it. Let thy mighty hande and out-ſtretched arme, O Lorde, bee ſtill our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, thy mercye and louing kindeneſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180838:19"/>in Ieſus Chriſt thy dear Sonne, oure ſaluation, thy true and holy word oure inſtruction, thy grace and holy ſpirite, our comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, vnto the ende and in the end, ſo be it.</p>
               <p>O Lord, increaſe our fayth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A PRAIER TO BE</hi> ſayde of the childe before he ſtudy his leſſon.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME. 119.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>Wherein ſhall the childe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe his way? In guiding him ſelfe according to thy Worde. Open myne eyes &amp;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180838:19"/>I ſhall knowe the maruails of thy Lawe. Giue me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and I ſhall keepe thy Lawe, yea, I ſhall keepe it with mine whole heart.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>LOrde, which art the fountain of all wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, ſeeing it hath pleaſed thee to giue mee the meane to bee taught in my youth for to learne to guide me godly and honeſtly all the courſe of my life, it maye alſo pleaſe thee to lighten myne vnderſtandinge, the which of it ſelfe is blind, that it may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:180838:20"/>and receiue that doctrine and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which ſhall bee taught me: it may pleaſe thee to ſtrengthen my memory to keep it wel: it maye pleaſe thee alſo to diſpoſe my hart wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to receiue it with ſuch deſire as appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: ſo that by my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude the occaſion which thou giueſt me, be not loſt. That I may thus do, it maye pleaſe thee to powre vpon me thine holy ſpirit, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite I ſay, of al vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, truth, iudgement, wiſdom &amp; learning, the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:180838:20"/>which maye make mee able ſo to profite, that the paines that ſhall be taken in teaching me, be not in vaine. And to what ſtudy ſoeuer I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye my ſelfe, make me, O lord, to addres it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right end: that is to know thee in oure Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that I may haue full truſt of ſaluation in thy grace, and to ſerue thee vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly according to thy pleaſure, ſo that whatſo euer I learne, it may be vnto me as an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to helpe me therevnto. and ſeing thou doſt pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:180838:21"/>to giue wiſdom to the little and humble ones, and to confound the proude in the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their wits, &amp; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to make thy ſelfe knowne to them that be of an vpright heart, and alſo to blinde the vngodly and wicked, I beſeech thee to faſhion me vnto true humility, ſo that I may be taught firſt to be obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and next vnto my ſuperiors, that thou haſte appoynted ouer me. Further that it may pleaſe thee to diſpoſe mine heart vnfaynedly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:180838:21"/>to ſeek thee and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all euill and filthye luſts of the fleſh: &amp; that in this ſort I may nowe prepare my ſelf to ſerue thee once in that eſtate which it ſhalpleaſe thee to appoint for me whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhall come to age.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A PRAIER TO BE</hi> ſayde before a man begin his worke.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME. 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>The Lorde reuealeth his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes vnto them that fear him, and maketh them to knowe his alliance.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O Lorde God moſte mercifull Father &amp;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:180838:22"/>ſauiour, ſeeing it hath pleaſed thee, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde vs to trauaile, that we may relieue our neede, we beſeech thee of thy grace ſo to bleſſe our labor that thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing may extende vnto vs, without the which we are not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue: &amp; that this great fauour may be a witnes vnto vs of thy bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; aſſiſtance, ſo that thereby we may know the fatherlye care that thou haſt ouer vs.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, O Lorde wee beſeech thee that thou wouldeſt ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:180838:22"/>vs with thy holye ſpirit, that we may faith fullye trauaile in our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate &amp; vocation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fraud or deceit: and that we maye indeuour oure ſelues to followe thine holy ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſeek to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy our greedy affections or deſire to gaine. And if it pleaſe our labour, giue vs a minde alſo to help the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue need according to that abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that thou of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye ſhalt giue vs: and knowing that all good thinges come of thee,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:180838:23"/>graunt that wee maye humble oure ſelues to our neighbours, &amp; not by any meanes lift our ſelues vp aboue them, which haue not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo liberal a portion as of thy mercye thou haſt giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs. And if it pleaſe thee to trye &amp; exerciſe vs by greter pouerty, and need then our fleſh would deſire, that thou wouldſt: yet O Lorde, grant vs grace to know that thou wilt nouriſh vs continually through thy bountifull liberality, that wee bee not ſo tempted that we
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:180838:23"/>fall not into diſtruſt: but that wee may pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently waite till thou fill vs, not onely with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall graces and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, but cheefely with thine heauenly &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall treaſures, to the intent that wee may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to giue thee thankes, and ſo wholly to reſt vppon thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes. Heare vs, O Lorde of mercy, through Ieſus Chriſte thy ſonne our Lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:180838:24"/>
               <head>APR AIER FOR <hi>the Morning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Gratious God, and louing Father, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, we do here pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent our ſelues before thy maieſtye, humblye proſtrating our ſelues before the throne of mercy, acknowledging and confeſſing from the bottome of our heartes that wee bee miſerable ſinners, dayly breaking thy commandementes, both in thought, word, and deede, wherein we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:180838:24"/>iuſtlye deſerue euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to be vtterly throwne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy preſence, yet O lord, we ſee thy goodnes againe towardes vs, who not ſuffering vs thus to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in our ſins, haſt ſent thine owne deare Son Ieſus Chriſt, to take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him whatſoeuer is due to reconcile and make vs at one with thee again: in him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, good Lorde, and throgh him do we com vnto thee, beſeeching thee for his ſake, that we feeling the greeuoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our ſins, and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:180838:25"/>vnder the burden of them, may feele the releaſe &amp; eaſe of them, in that we be thorough thy holy ſpirit aſſured, and ſtedfaſtly beleeue, that Chriſt hath borne the burden of them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for vs. Graunt, O Lorde, that wee being aſſured hereof in oure conſciences, may tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough thy holye ſpirite be renued in the inner man, to hate, deteſt and abhorre ſinne, and to ſtudy to liue according to thy bleſſed will du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our whole life.</p>
               <p>We do not only pray
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:180838:25"/>for our ſelues, but alſo for all thy whol church, eſpecially ſuch as bee perſecuted for thi word graunt vnto them, that whether it be by death or life, they may glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye thy name to theire liues end. Bee mercifull to this Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Irelande, wee beſech thee good lord, and preſerue euery part &amp; member of the ſame, eſpecially thy ſeruaunt ELIZABETH oure Queene: graunt her all ſuch giftes as be neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for ſo high a calling, to the aduancement of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:180838:26"/>thy glory, and benefite of this commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, to the eſtabliſhing of a perfect gouernment of thy Church, according to the preſcript rule of thy bleſſed word, to the rooting out of al ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and reliques of Antichriſt, to the gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of her ſubiectes in all peace and traquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Defend her, O lord, from all conſpiracies, treaſons, &amp; rebellions, and ſo woorke in the harts of all her ſubiects, that knowing her au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorise doth come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy heauenly maieſtie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:180838:26"/>they may with obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t harts humbly obey her in thee &amp; for thee. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the whol counſell &amp; the. Magiſtrats of the realme, that being ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened through thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite, they maye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thy truth, ſuppreſſe wickednes, &amp; maintain equity. Beholde all the Paſtors &amp; Preachers of the worde, bleſſe their labours, increaſe the number of them, place ouer euerye Church a painfull watch man, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue all idle lubbers, &amp; confound the power of Antichriſt, &amp; tourne
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:180838:27"/>the heartes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that they may be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to thy trueth. Bleſſe the two Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, Cambridge and Oxenforde, and all the Studentes of the ſame, with all Schooles of learning. Beholde all thoſe that bee afflicted with any kind of croſſe, that they may profit by thy correction in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, for our ſelues heere gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee heartily craue at thy handes, that it woulde pleaſe thee to make vs thankfull vnto
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:180838:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>thy maieſtie, for all thy louing kindnes ſhewed vnto vs euen from our infancy: eſpecially, that thou haſte this preſent night deliuered vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all dangers both of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, wherinto many haue fallen, as we in like maner ſhoulde haue doone, if wee had not beene ſtayed with thy merciful hand: that thou haſt alſo graunted vnto vs ſo ſweet &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortable reſte, and haſte now preſently brought vs to the beginning of this daye. For theſe thinges, good Lord, we
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:180838:28"/>yeelde vnto thee moſte harty thanks, beſehcing thee to make vs more &amp; more daylye thankfull vnto thy maieſtye for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; pardon oure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes. And as thou haſt ſafely preſerued vs vnto this preſenthowre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the daungers of this life: ſo we beſeech thee continue thy fauor towardes vs this day, &amp; the whole courſe of our life. Defend vs, O lord, that we now entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the affayres of this daye, bee not drawne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the vayne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:180838:28"/>of this world, to ſinn and wickednes: that we walk not in the ſhadowes of death, that we be not intangled in the ſnares of ſinne, that wee ſtumble not at the blockes of iniqnity, that we finallye fall not into the pit of death, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but being ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed vnderthy wings we may cheerfully and conſtantlye goe on for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the end of our courſe. Graunt vnto vs, O Lorde our God, that this good time which thou granteſt vnto vs in this life, bee not idly, or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:180838:29"/>vainly of vs conſumed, but that euerye one of vs maye bee diligentlye exerciſed in his calling this day, and all our life long, being aſſured that thou wilt once call vs to yeelde an account of our ſtewardſhip. Indue vs we beſech thee, with thoſe giftes and graces, which bee needfull for vs in our calling, &amp; that with a pure and ſincere conſcience we may vſe them to the benefite of our brethren, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of our own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, before thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty. We beſeech thee,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:180838:29"/>O Lord, that in all oure confultations, words &amp; works this day, and the whole courſe of oure life, wee maye alwayes haue thee preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, knowing that thou ſeeſt euen the very deepe thoughts of our harts, which alwais maye bee as a brydle to pull vs backe, that wee neither do, nor yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto anye ſinne or wickednes, but that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes we may be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in the affayres of this life, that we loke ſtill to the ende of our courſe, when it ſhall
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:180838:30"/>pleaſe thee to bring vs through the pilgrimage of this life to our euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reſte with thy deare Sonne IESVS CHRIST oure Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. In whole name for theſe mercies and what ſoeuer thou knoweſt to be needefull for vs, and for the whole Church, we pray vnto thee, as he him ſelfe hath taught vs in his holye worde, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Our father. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Lorde bleſſe vs and ſaue vs, the Lorde make his face to ſhyne vppon vs, and be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto vs, the Lorde
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:180838:30"/>tourne his fauourable countenaunce towards vs, &amp; grant vs his peace. The grace of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, the loue of God the Father, &amp; the moſte comfortable fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippe of the holye Ghoſte, be with vs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and keepe vs this day and euermore. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A CONFESSION</hi> of ſinnes with faith and repentance.</head>
               <p>O Merciful and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye Father, wee
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:180838:31"/>thy ſeruaunts do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly proſtrate our ſelues before thy maieſtye, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging heere in thy ſight our hainous offences committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy maieſtye, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and beholding thy heauye wrath againſte them: wee feele oure ſelues laden (O Lorde our God) with a huge companye of horrible ſinnes, wherof euen the verye leaſte, beeing but conceiued in thought, is ſufficient in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to throw vs down to the euerlaſting bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lake. Our owne
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:180838:31"/>conſciences, O Lorde, do beare witnes againſt vs, of oure manyfolde tranſgreſſions of thy bleſſed law, of our ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity &amp; ſenceleſſe blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes running head-long to deſtruction, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſinne after ſinne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not notorious to the world, yet horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before thine eye. The thoughtes of oure hartes riſe vp in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt vs: the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of our talke before thy maieſtye condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs: the wickednes of our deedes from thy ſight reiecteth vs: al our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:180838:32"/>wicked thoghts, words and deeds, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward corruption of our nature, do altogeather as it were a whole lump and loade of ſinne, lye heauie vppon vs, and with their intollerable weight do euen preſſe vs down to hell. Wee do daylye grone vnder the burthen of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly lamenting our owne folly ſo greedily running into them. In Heauen, Earth, or Hel, wee ſee none able to ſuſtaine the weight of them, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye beloued Sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:180838:32"/>Chrſt, who in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy infinite, and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion endleſſe, hath ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and ouer come that endleſſe punniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due vnto them: in him therefore in him, moſt meeifull father &amp; through him wee come to thee, being fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured according to thy promiſe, that thou wilt accept and take that ful recompence which hee thy deere Sonne hath made for vs, as a iuſt raunſome for all the ſinnes of all thoſe who with a true faith take houlde on him.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:180838:33"/>
               <p>In him therefore we ſee thine anger towards vs appeaſed, thy wrath ſatisfied, and our debts payde.</p>
               <p>Increaſe in vs, good Lord, we beſeech thee, this liuely and feeling faith, for wee feele it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes in vs verye weake, &amp; troubled with many doubtes: increaſe it in vs (O Lorde) that wee may through thy holy ſpirite bee aſſured that the punniſhement of our ſinnes is fully in thy ſonne diſcharged. Make vs, O Lorde our God, to feele this ſame
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:180838:33"/>in our ſoules and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that IESVS CHRIST is ours, and all that hee hath done: that we are graffed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his body, and made one with him, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fellow heires with him of euerlaſting life. Let vs not onely haue theſe wordes in our mouthes (good Lord) but through thy holye ſpirite lette vs feele the comfort of them in our heartes fully ſealed and ſetled in vs: that we fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our ſelues inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before thy iudgment ſeat, diſcharged and our
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:180838:34"/>conſciences towardes thee appeaſed, may bee ſwallowed vp with an vnfained loue towarde thy heauenly Maieſtie, and towardes thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for thy ſake. Make ſin to dye in vs dayly more &amp; more, that we may hate, deteſt, &amp; vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly abhor all ſin and wickedneſſe in all men, but eſpeciallye in oure ſelues: that wee maye ſtrongly thorough thy holye ſpirite ſette our ſelues in open warre &amp; defiance againſt all ſinn and wickedneſſe: that we pleaſe not ourſelues
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:180838:34"/>in our ſinnes, but ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye examining ſin by the iuſt rule of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lawes, wee maye vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly from the bottom of our hearts condemn euen the leaſte ſinne in our ſelues, hauinge our whole ioy, comfort and conſolation vppon thoſe thinges whiche bee agreeable to thy bleſſed will, alwayes beeing afrayde to doe any thing contrarye to the ſame: that we may euen from the bottom of our hearts examine and try our thoughtes, before thy preſence,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:180838:35"/>that they be vpright &amp; vnfayned, not hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall in outwarde ſhew onely and appearance, but that euen all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of our harts being opened and diſcloſed before thee, we maye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as though it were openly before the face of the whole worlde bring them in ſhewe, knowing that a dubble hart is deteſtable in thin eyes: and that we may walke alwaies as before thine eyes, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of man, beeing more careful to walke circumſpectlye,

<pb n="63" facs="tcp:180838:35"/>in this reſpect, that wee haue thee to be a vewer of our doinges, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande folde more then the eyes of man: that thus we maye walke as becommeth thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, not onely in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſhew, but alſo in ſincerity of hart, abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring euen the leaſt ſinn in our ſelues, ſtryuing, reſiſting and fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, not deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelues in ſinne, nor noriſhing the ſame in our breſt, but earneſt lye embracing, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſlye ſeeking after thoſe thinges which be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:180838:36"/>pleaſant in thine eyes: that neither the feare of man, nor loſſe of goods life, landes, poſſeſſions, or friends draw vs away from thee, to doe anye leaſt thing contrarye to thy will and pleaſure: neither the fauoure or friendſhip of man, nor yet the flattering entice mentes of this worlde, nor the vaine promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſame doe moue vs any whit from the true and endles ioy, delighte and pleaſure which we ought to haue in thoſe thinges which be agreeable to thy wil,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:180838:36"/>and the conſtaunt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the ſame: but that alwayes to the end of our lyfe we may continue in thy pathes, growing and increaſing from faith to faith, from ſtrength to ſtrength, till at length we ſhall come to thy euerlaſting reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A FORME OF</hi> MOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning praier neceſſarye for this preſent time for godly chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to vſe in their houſes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</head>
               <p>WE moſt humblye thank thee O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:180838:37"/>Father) for the ſweete &amp; quiet reſt that we haue had this night, for the louing and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable deliueraunce out of all dangers both of bodye and Soule, which we iuſtly deſerue to be throwne into for our manyfolde ſinnes: for that thou haſte ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs vp this morning, we pray thee to goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs: and for as much as thou ſeeſt our ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhnes and drowſines, it woulde pleaſe thee (good Lord) to pull vs after thee, and to ſhewe vs thoſe wayes, which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:180838:37"/>thou haſt appoynted vs to walk in. And as thou renueſt this morning, ſo renue thy mercies: and as thou cauſeſt the Sun comfortablye to ſhine to our bodilye eyes, ſo vouchſafe (wee praye thee) to be Sunne vnto our bodyes and to our ſoules, by the beames of thy holy Spirite, and Starre of thy bleſſed Word, ſhining into the middeſt of our harts, to driue away all the night and darknes of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe: to chaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all want of true feare of thy good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:180838:38"/>and in place ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, bring in loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes thy glory, zeale of thy houſe, loue alſo towardes our brethren: eſpeciallye thoſe that thou aboue the reſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeſt vnto vs, that we may loue them with that loue, wherewithall thou haſt firſt loued vs: which is pure, vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, vehement, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting: and therfore we praye thee to ridde our hartes of all naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and corrupt loue, and whatſoeuer is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete to bee in thoſe veſſels that are to ſerue
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:180838:38"/>ſuch a mightye Prince as thou arte: and in thoſe houſes wherein it pleaſeth thy maieſtye by thy holye Spirite to dwell: and therefore on the other ſide (good Lord) chace away from vs all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rancor and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, all pride, enuiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diſdaynefulneſſe, vncharitableneſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturalneſſe, vnkinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and whatſoeuer is contrarye to that loue, wherof thou haſt giuen vs a liuelye example in our ſaniour Ieſus chriſt: vnto the which exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, grant (good Lord)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:180838:39"/>that wee may alwayes haue oure eyes lifted vp, and therein holden, and cauſed thereby to profit, vntill ſuch time as we come to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, wherunto thou haſt appointed we ſhall come. Vouchſafe more ouer by the comming of the ſelfe ſame Spirit, to ſcatter in vs all the night and darkneſſe of ignoraunce, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and of all thoſe things which pertaine to the clearer and fuller knowledge of thy truth Take from vs all negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, all want of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:180838:39"/>and diſcretion, &amp; deliuer vs from al thoſe thinges, which thou knoweſt to bee hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunces to vs, either to walke in that great cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge of Chriſtianitye whervnto thou haſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs, or in thoſe ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges wherin thou haſt placed euery one of vs: that we maye walke ſo (good Lorde) both in the one &amp; in the other, that thy name maye be glorified in both.</p>
               <p>We praye not onely for our ſelues (O moſte merciful Father) but for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:180838:40"/>all thoſe that thou haſt appointed to eternall life: beſeechinge thee to gather the number of thoſe that are to bee gathered; thoſe that thou haſte alreadye cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, thou wouldeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes keepe: and to this end (good Lorde) rayſe vp faithfull mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters both of thy church and common weale, whoſe heartes thou wouldeſt fyll with all graces of thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit meete for their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, meete alſo for theſe dangerous times: roote out from among
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:180838:40"/>thy church, al rauening and deuouring beaſts, which to fyll their own bellies, diſtroy thy flok, eaſe thy ſelfe of all hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings &amp; idle ſhepherds, which haue no care nor skil to feed thi flok with the holſom food of thy bleſſed worde, nor to rule them with that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitye, wherewithall thou wilte haue thy people to bee ruled: thoſe Paſtoures that thou haſte giuen, it woulde pleaſe thee to increaſe the number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: thoſe that are falne a ſleepe &amp; caried away
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:180838:41"/>with the corruptions of theſe times, that thou wouldeſt awake, letting them vnderſtande the charge that thou haſte mitted vnto them, the truſt that thou haſt put them in, and the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt that thou wilt take at their handes. Be grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (O Lord) vnto this land of ours, and enter not into iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the horrible ſinnes of it, namelye, the contempt and light eſteeming of thy holy word, ſo many yeares offered vnto vs, and wee beeing truſted withall, ſo manye Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:180838:41"/>better then we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed by, whiche woulde haue brought foorth the fruite therof more then weehaue done: and we not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue brought foorth no good fruite, but rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and vnſauourye, to prouoke thy Maieſtye withall: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding all theſe our ſinnes, it woulde pleaſe thee in that loue, wherewithall thou haſt firſt loued vs, when we hated thee, &amp; in that long patience wherein thou haſte hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto borne with vs, and doeſt yet beare and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:180838:42"/>tarrieſt for ourrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: to grant vs hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and earneſtrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, our heartes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing effectually touched with thy holye Spirite, ſtrikinge theſerockye hearts of ours, that thei maye bee reſolued into riuers of teares for oure ſynnes, making them ſoft and meeke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the print of thy holy word, and ſeale of thy bleſſed ſpirire, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with thy fynger thine own laws in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo, that thou maiſt read thine owne hande, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thine owne
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:180838:42"/>ſeale, &amp; ſo paſſe by vs, when thou ſhalt bring thy iudgement vppon the face of the earth, for the iniquities thereof: whereof thou haſte gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſtill giueſt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time diuers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, which we beſeech thee may be profitable vnto vs, whilſte firſt of al we acknowledge thy hande ſtriking vs, and thy counſayle callinge vs thereby torepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, that thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uier iudgementes doe not fall vpon vs, to our vtter deſtruction.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:180838:43"/>
               <p>Moreouer, we thank thee (O Lorde) for that it hath pleaſed thee to be the watch-ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and as it were the ſpie of this Church and common wealth, and haſte fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene all the ſtormes, &amp; treaſons comming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte it, and againſte thine annoynted oure Souaraigne, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e thou in mercye haſt appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to rule ouer it, and haſt ſcattered them and brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to naught, and haſte purſued cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of thine enemyes and ours vnto death, be ſeeching thee to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:180838:43"/>this watchfull and carefull eye ouer vs, ſtill to doe vs good, and to purſue the reſt of thine enemies and ours vnto the graue: giuing not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto them, vnto whom thou haſte left place of repentaunce. And to this ende, raiſe vp the harts of our moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous QVEENE &amp; her honourable Counſell thy Magiſtrates, that as they ſit in thy ſeate, and are called by thy name, ſo they maye execute thy iuſtice, which thou ſo well approoueſt of,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:180838:44"/>whereof alſo thou wilt require a ſtraighte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt at their hands. Wee deſire thee alſo to ſhewe theſe thy graces to all other Churches of thine, namely, thy Church of Englande, that it may enioye that peace that thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it: and graunt that the ſame be referred to that end wherfore thou haſt giuen it: namelye, to the ful eſtabliſhment of the throne of thy dear ſonn our Sauiour IESVS CHRIST, &amp; to the building of his Kingdome there. Wee
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:180838:44"/>beſech thee alſo, for the churches which thi ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hath pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted long ſince, eſpeciallye thoſe, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue receiued knowledge in time of our ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, places of refuge in time of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: that it woulde pleaſe thee to continue thy louing kindnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cauſe them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their faith toward thee, &amp; obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy holy worde. And whenſoeuer it ſhal bee thy pleaſure, to try them with any kinde of affliction, it woulde
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:180838:45"/>pleaſe thee to graunt vnto them, that they maye put their truſte in thee, hauing regarde to the truth of thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to the good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that they haue of thy helpe in times paſt, and thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue comfort &amp; hope, (O Lorde) euen of life in death, and of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in deſtruction. We praye thee alſo (good lord) that we may haue the feeling of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our brethren, as members of the ſame body, &amp; thoſe that liue by the ſame ſpirite. And
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:180838:45"/>therefore we pray thee, that according to the manyfold troubles that thou ſhalt viſite them with, it woulde bee thy good pleaſure, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out rhy grace in ſuch plentifull maner, that thy children maye patiently beare, and ioy fullye attende, for the good howre wherein thou wilt pul them out of all their troubles. And eſpecially we pray thy maieſty for our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that are afflicted for thy Goſpell ſake: namelye, thoſe that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer impriſonment or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:180838:46"/>in any nation, for the clearer teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of it: that it woulde pleaſe thee to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patience in all theire troubles, wiſedom and mouthes to defend thy cauſe, againſt all thoſe that riſe vp againſte it: that thou woldſt bleſſe their trauels and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, for that for which they are taken: which is, to giue a freer courſe of thy goſpel into al pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. And therewithall wee beeſeeche thee for the churches of France and Flaunders, which are ſo miſerably racked
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:180838:46"/>and torn in ſunder, and which are almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with theſe fierie trials: that it wold pleſe thee to looke vpon the ſighings and gronings, the teares that fall from their eies continually, the bloud that is ſhed in all the partes of the Lande, the bodies that lye vnburied, to bee meate to the foules of the ayre, and Fiſhes of the Sea, the lonenes of wiues lacking ther huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, children their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; euery frend his freind. And for aſmuch as thoſe thynges are
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:180838:47"/>come vppon them for thy names ſake, let it be thy good pleaſure to helpe them conſidering that they are forſaken of all their friends rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about: and therefore praye thee that thou wouldeſt not looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our ſinnes, nor the ſins of our forefathers, wherby we deſerue not onelye this correction, but vtter deſtruction, as Sodom &amp; Gomorrha: but rather to looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy mercies which were before them: whereby thou haſt ſayde, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we doe offend,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:180838:47"/>and thou doeſt correct vs, yet thou wilt not take awaye thy mercies from vs, but wilt leaue a remnant which thou wilt multiply, and make as the ſtarres of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and as the ſandes of the ſea. Looke alſo (O lord) vpon the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſnes and cruelty, vnfaithfulnes, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of the enemies, wherewithal they blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thee, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke thee to thy face, and therefore in thine owne cauſe, and for thine own ſake, take the matter into thine owne
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:180838:48"/>handes, and pay into the Boſomes of thine enymies double and treble of that they haue giuen to thee. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt them, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to thine holy ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, haſten their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that afterward thy iudgement may haſten vpon the earth, and the inhabitants therof may learn to knowe thee by thy iudgementes; that would not vnderſtand and come to thee, by the louing callinge of thy Goſpell. Wee pray thee (O Lorde) for our
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:180838:48"/>brethren that are vp in arms in both thoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: that thou wouldſt goe before them, and come behinde them, and on euerye ſyde of them: couer their heads in the daye of battell, teache their handes to fyght, &amp; their fingers to war: giue them wiſdom &amp; valiantnes, and good ſucces in al their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes: ſtrike a dizineſſe &amp; maze of ſpirite into the enimies hearts, and take away from them al force, and diſappoint all their counſels. And vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our brethren in Fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:180838:49"/>we beſeeche thee that thou wouldeſt comfort them ouer all thy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and breaches that haue beene made in vpon them: &amp; where there are new forces e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day gathered, new ſleights inuented to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it maye pleaſe thee, to ſcatter their forces, and bring their ſleights to nothing. Yea grant alſo (O lord) that that which they haue deuiſed againſt thy chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, may come vppon their own heades. And for oure Brethren in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:180838:49"/>Fraunce wee beſeeche thee (O Lorde) what ſtraights ſo euer thei be in, thou wouldeſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them: and althogh they be forſaken in the iudgement of all the world, and in their own iudgementes, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danding thou that haſt the iſſues of death in thine owne handes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer thoſe that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to death. And finally we moſt humbly thanke thee, for that it hath pleaſed thee to keepe vs this daye, and all the dayes and times of our liues, beſeeching
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:180838:50"/>thee, that thou wouldſt receiue vs this night in to thy holye keeping, that we may haue qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et reſt, not of bodies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but of our ſoules alſo, reſtinge from all thoſe thinges that are contrarye to thy moſt holy wil, ate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding while thou raiſeſt vs vp in the morning, to do al thoſe thinges that thou haſt appointed vs. Theſe thinges wee deſire of thee, &amp; all other things (which thou knoweſt to bee more needfull for vs, and thy whole Church, better then we
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:180838:50"/>ourſelues do know) for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake: ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame praier, that hee hym ſelfe hath taught vs. Our father. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A forme of euening prayer, neceſſary to be vſed of all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in their houſes and families.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 55. verſ. 16.</bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>I vvill call vnto GOD, and the Lord vvill ſaue me: Euening &amp; Morning, and at noone will I pray &amp; make a noiſe, and hee vvill he are my voice.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>VVE moſtehum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye beſeeche thee, O gratious God and heauenlye Father,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:180838:51"/>euen for thy ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſtes ſake, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and forgiue vs all our ſinnes, in thought, worde and deede com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt thy holy lawes and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, to tourne away from vs gratiouſlye all thoſe plagues which we moſt iuſtlye haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for them, both in this lyfe and in the lyfe to come, working in our harts euery day by the holye ſpirite more true and vnfayned ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter care euer hereafter to know thy bleſſed wil
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:180838:51"/>reuealed in thy worde, and to order all our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and doings ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame, &amp; ſo much the rather, O Lorde, becauſe of thy manyfolde bleſſinges, wherby thou doſt day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mooue vs herevnto, for the which (O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye father) make vs more hartely thankfull, ſpecially for our recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the firſte after thine owne holineſſe &amp; righteouſneſſe, for our redemption by IESVS CHRIST, when wee were vtterly loſte, for that knowledge of our
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:180838:52"/>Sauiour, which by the preaching of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Goſpell thorough thy holye Spirite thou haſte wrought in oure heartes, for true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, for fayth, hope, and loue, for watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in oure dooinges, and all other gyftes of thy grace pertayninge to oure ſaluation, all which graces (O Lord) are verye weake in vs, becauſe of the greate wickedneſſe of oure heartes ſtriuing againſt thy holy ſpirite, ſo as in thy wrath thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:180838:52"/>iuſtlye forſake vs vtterly: (yet O Lorde) let it bee thy grations pleaſure to increaſe them in oure heartes euerye daye, euen ſo long as we lyue in this worlde, as of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thou haſte begun, that thereby the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of oure ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on maye be more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynelye ſealed vppe vnto oure owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that ſo wee maye alſo learne to bee more truelye thankfull vnto thy MAIESTIE for the benefites of this lyfe: Namelye,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:180838:53"/>that thou haſt hitherto euer ſince wee were borne, giuen vs thoſe thinges that were need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for oure bodies, as health, foode apparrell, and ſuch like, that thou haſt kept vs from many daungers, comfort vs in all our troubles, and ſtrengthen vs in all our weakneſſe, and giuing vs grace this daye to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour faithfully &amp; true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in our callinges, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brought vs ſafelye paſte all the daungers thereof, vnto this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent howre. O Lorde forgiue vs the ſinnes of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:180838:53"/>this daye, and of oure whole life, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye our great vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for theſe thy manifold bleſſings, and in IESVS CHRIST thy deare ſonne, continue them towardes vs euer hereafter both in ſoules and bodies, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye this night receiue vs into thy bleſſed kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, preſerue vs from all daungers, from ſin, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al vngodly dreames and fanſies, graunting vnto vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable reſt, ſo as wee maye bee the better ſtrengthened to ſerue thee faithfully in
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:180838:54"/>our calling, and giuing vs grace alwayes both ſleeping and waking, to bee readye when thou ſhalt call vs out of this miſerable worlde. Laſt of all, becauſe thou haſt commanded vs to pray for others alſo, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee good Lorde be mercifull to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſpecially to thoſe Churches where thy Goſpell is truely prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, continue thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy towards this realme, preſerue oure Queene, bleſſe her Counſell, and all in aucthoritye with neceſſarye graces,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:180838:54"/>increaſe the number of faythfull Preachers, ſtrengthen the Godly, lighten the ignoraunt, conuert the wicked, be merciful vnto al ſcholes and places of learning, to all our friendes and kinsfolkes, and others, afflicted in bodye or in ſoule, graunting to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye one of them, as to oure ſelues, thoſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye graces whiche thou knoweſte to bee needfull for euery one of vs in oure ſeuerall eſtates and callinges, to the glorye of thy name, and the better
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:180838:55"/>aſſurance of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through CHRIST IESVS, in whoſe name we aske of thy maieſty as hee hath taught vs. Our Father. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Euening prayer for priuate houſes and families.</head>
               <p>O Gratious God, and louing Father, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, wee doe heere preſente our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy maieſty, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly proſtrating our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues before the throne of mercy, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:180838:55"/>and confeſſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bottome of oure heartes that we be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinners, daylye breaking thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, bothe in thought, word, &amp; deed, wherein wee iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue euerlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and to be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thrown from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence: yet, O Lorde, we ſee thy goodnes again towardes vs, who not ſuffering vs thus to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in our ſinnes, haſte ſent thine owne deare ſon Ieſus Chriſt, to take vppon him whatſoeuer is due, to reconcile and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:180838:56"/>make vs at owne with thee agayne: In hym therefore, good Lorde, &amp; through him do wee come vnto the, beſech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the for his ſake, that wee feeling the gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſneſſe of our ſinnes and groning vnder the burthen of them, maye feele the releaſe &amp; eaſe of them, in that wee be through thy holy ſpirit aſſured, and ſteadfaſtly beleeue, that Chriſte hath born the burthen of them, eaueu for vs. Graunte O Lorde, that we beeing aſſured here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in our conſciences,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:180838:56"/>maye through thy holy Spirit bee renuee in the inner man, to hate, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and abhorre ſinne, and to ſtudie to liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to thy bleſſed will duringe our whole life.</p>
               <p>Wee do not onelye pray for our ſelues, but alſo for all thy whole Churche, eſpeciallye ſuch as bee perſecuted for thy worde: graunt vnto them, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee thy death or life, they may glorify thy name to their liues end. Be merciful to this
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:180838:57"/>Church of England &amp; Irelande, wee beſeeche thee good Lorde, to preſerue euery part and member of the ſame, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially thy ſeruant E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIZABETH our queen: graunt her all ſuch gifts as bee needefull for ſo high a calling, to the aduauncement of thy glory, and benefite of this common wealth, to the eſtabliſhiſhing of a perfect gouerment of thy Church, according to the preſcript rule of thy bleſſed word, to the rooting out of al ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and reliques of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:180838:57"/>Antichriſte, to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning of her ſubiects in al peace and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Defende her, O Lorde, from all conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, treaſons, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, and ſo worke in the heartes of all her ſubiectes, that knowing her authoritye dothe come from thy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maieſtye, they may with obedient heartes humblye obey her in thee and for thee. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, and all the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of the realm, that being lightned through thy holye ſpirite, they
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:180838:58"/>maye defend thy truth, ſuppreſſe wickedneſſe, and maintaine equitie. Beholde all the Paſtors and Preachers of the worde, bleſſe their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, increaſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, place ouer euery Churche a paineful watchman, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue all idle Lubbers &amp; confound the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Antichriſte, and turne the heartes of the people that they maye be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to thy truth Bleſſe the two Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, Cambridge and Oxenforde, and all the Studentes of the ſame,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:180838:58"/>with al Schooles of ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Beholde all thoſe that bee afflicted with any kinde of croſſe, that they may profit by thy correction in newneſſe of lyfe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, for our ſelues here gathered, wee ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der moſt hearty thanks to thy maieſtie, O Lord which haſt hitherto fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our infancye, preſerued vs by thy mercie from all perils and daungers both of ſoule and body whervnto fraile man is ſubiect, that thou haſte ſent vno vs all thinges neceſſary for this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:180838:59"/>life, as health, foode, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and ſuche like, which manye of thy dear children do want, being notwithſtanding as preciouſely boughte with the precious blod of thy deare Sonne, as we be, &amp; yet lye in my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and calamity, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with pouertye, nakedneſſe, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and baniſhment, in which caſe alſo, dear Father, thou mighteſt haue brought vs, ſaue onelye that thou dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt heerein more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably with vs, then with them. For the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:180838:59"/>which thy louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, we giue thee har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thanks, deſiring thee, that as thou haſt hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thus fauourablye in mercy preſerued vs by thy protection, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen preſently this daye haſte brought vs paſt al the dangers thereof: ſo we beſeeche thee good Lord, in like fauour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold vs this night, that we taking our naturall reſt and quietneſſe, may thorough thy protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bee defended, that our bodyes reſting, our ſouls may be occupied in beholding thy fauor
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:180838:60"/>and mercy toward thy children, ſtil looking for the comming of Lorde and Sauioure hs IESYS CHRIST for oure full redemption. Grant that our ſleepe bee not immoderate, according to the luſt of our fleſhe, but as much as is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to refreſhe oure weake nature: that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus refreſhed both the body and the mind maye bee more able to do their ſeuerall office and function, in that vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation wherein thou haſt placed vs.</p>
               <p>Graunt that we lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:180838:60"/>our bodies downe to reſt, maye bee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by put in mind of oure long reſt of death: that as we do now lai down our bodies in bedde, ſo wee maye bee thereby admoniſhed, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after they ſhall bee laid downe in graue, to bee conſumed to Duſte, Earth, and Aſhes, from whence they were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. That wee hauing this before oure eyes, maye bee ſtyrred vpp in minde warelye to walke in this our pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grymage, not knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:180838:61"/>when the time ſhal be of our departure, but alwayes to bee founde ready with our lampes of our pure faith cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burning, that we may bee accepted to meete the Bridegrome, when our mortal, earthly, and corruptible bodies ſhal be made like to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body of our lord and ſauiour Chriſt Ieſu, there to raigne with him in perpetuall ioye and conſolation togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the elect children of God, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually lauding with all the heauenly multitude

<pb n="115" facs="tcp:180838:61"/>the glorious maieſty of thee our Lord God &amp; heauenly Father, in our Lorde and ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt. For theſe and whatſoeuer elſe thou knoweſt to be needfull for vs and thy whole Church, we praye vnto thee, as he him ſelf hath taught vs, ſaying: Our Father. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Lorde bleſſe vs and ſaue vs, the Lorde make his face to ſhine vpon vs, and be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto vs: the Lord tourne his fauourable countenaunce vnto vs, and grant vs his peace.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:180838:62"/>The grace of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, the loue of God the Father, &amp; the moſte comfortable fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippe of the holye Ghoſte, be with vs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and keepe vs this day and euermore. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A forme of euening prayer, neceſſary to be vſed of all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in their houſes and families.</head>
               <p>O Lorde prepare our hartes to pray, bow down thine eares (deare Father) and heare vs, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen thine eyes &amp; looke vppon vs for thy deare
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:180838:62"/>Son Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, and receiue our humble confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we make to thee againſte our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, which haue broken all thy lawes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſerue to hauethy heauy iudgments pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon our heades to our vtter deſtruction, if thou ſhouldeſt enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement with the leaſte of oure ſinnes, whereof wee haue ſo great and infinite thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands: notwithſtanding we praye thee to turne away thy face from our ſinnes, and for IESVS CHRISTES ſake to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:180838:63"/>forgiue vs all that is paſt, and graunt that we may haue the aſſurance of the forgiuenes of our ſinnes, ſealed vp by thy holy ſpirite in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, whereby we knowing that we are at one with thee, maye haue our harts kindled with thy loue ſo fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently, as it maye waſte in vs all that is againſte thy holy will. And for this cauſe we beſeech thee, good Lord, to go forward with the work of our new byrth, that thou haſte begunne in vs, and neuer take away
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:180838:63"/>thy hande, vntill ſuch time as thou haſt made an end of it: and to this end, we beſeech thee to ſlaye in vs euerye daye, more and more the old man with his concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences, nailing them to the croſſe of thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt: and cauſing vs to feele the power of his paſſion in our bodies and in oure ſoules, that we beeing partakers thereof, maye come alſo to the felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of thy holye reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: not onelye in that we ſhall once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before thee, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:180838:64"/>theſe our baſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies chaunged, and made like vnto his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodye, but alſo that wee maye in the mean time riſe from the death of ſin to all new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, and that our good works may ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing them may glorify thee our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father: not only they that are of the ſelf ſame Religion with vs, but but thoſe alſo that are enimies vnto thy truth, may rather in the time of their calling by the voyce of thy Goſpell,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:180838:64"/>yeeld themſelues to be one ſheepfold with vs. And we moſte humbly thank thee (O Heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father) for all thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kyndeneſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vppon vs from time to time, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for that olde and ancient Loue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall thou haſt loued vs before the beginng of the worlde: for that alſo that thou calling vs by the voyce of thy Holye Goſpell in that good tyme that thou appoyntedſt for vs, haſt giuen vs faith, hope, and loue, and all other
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:180838:65"/>graces which thou kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt to bee needfull for vs: which we beſeeche thee to increaſe in vs with mighty increaſes, according to that thou ſeeſt we haue neede of, hauing regarde to oure manifold enemies, that wee haue to wreſtle with: and that we haue not to ſtriue with fleſhe and bloud, but againſte the Diuels themſelues. And therefore conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their ſtrength, and our weakeneſſe, their craft and oure ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, their watchfulneſſe and oure ſluggiſhneſſe,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:180838:65"/>their long experience and our rawneſſe, their preparation &amp; our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and that wee haue not only nothing to helpe vs, but alſo to carry about vs our own concupiſcences, readye to betraye vs into the handes of our enemies, it maye pleaſe thee to furniſh vs from aboue, giuing vs the ſtrength of thy holy ſpirit, in the inner man, reaching vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the compleat har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we beeing armed on both ſides, maye be prepared at all aſſaies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:180838:66"/>all aſſaults of our enemies. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as in this weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wee oftentimes giue backe, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times runne away, wee pray thee (O Lord) that with the hand of faith, wee may lay holde on the victory of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt: that albeit we be not able to ouercome in our owne perſons, yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding we may ouercom in his, who hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commed for vs all, &amp; ſo bee partakers of thoſe promiſes that thou haſt knit vnto that glorious
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:180838:66"/>victory. And we moſt humblye thanke thee alſo for thoſe graces both of the bodye and ſoule, which pertaine to this preſent life: deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thee to increaſe them vppon vs, and in vs, ſo farre foorth as thou ſeeſt wee haue neede of to thy glory, the commodity of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and our owne comforts: therfore we beſeech thee, Lord, to teach vs with thy holy Spirite the lawfull vſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not ſuffer our harts to bee rooted in them,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:180838:67"/>but that at all times we maye be willing to part from them. And when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe thee to call for vs, wee may willingly goe vnto thee, as childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their deare Fathers, ſtrangers vnto their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and members of the body vnto their Head: and ſo much the glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by how much thou Lord art better then all the men in the worlde, and the kingdome that thou haſt prepared, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes thereof.</p>
               <p>We pray not only for
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:180838:67"/>our ſelues (O moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father) but for all thoſe that thou haſt appointed to eternall life: beſeechinge thee to gather the number of thoſe that are to bee gathered; thoſe that thou haſte alreadye cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, thou wouldeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes keepe: and to this end (good Lorde) rayſe vp faithfull mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters both of thy church and common weale, whoſe heartes thou wouldeſt fyll with the graces of thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit meete for their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, meete alſo for
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:180838:68"/>theſe dangerous times: roote out from among thy church, al rauening and deuouring beaſts, which to fyll their own bellies, diſtroy thy flok, eaſe thy ſelfe of all hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings &amp; idle ſhepherds, which haue no care nor skil to feed thi flok with the holſom food of thy bleſſed worde, nor to rule them with that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitye, wherewithall thou wilte haue thy people to bee ruled: thoſe Paſtoures that thou haſte giuen, it woulde pleaſe thee to increaſe the number of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:180838:68"/>them, thoſe that are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len aſleepe and carried awaye with the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of theſe tymes, that thou wouldeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, letting them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande the charge that thou haſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them, the truſt that thou haſt put them in, and the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt that thou wilt take at their handes. Be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious (O Lorde) vnto this lande of ours, and enter not into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the horrible ſins of it, namely, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt &amp; light eſteming of thy holye worde, ſo
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:180838:69"/>many yeares offred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, and we being tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted withall, ſo manye nations better then we being paſſed by, which woulde haue brought foorth the fruit thereof more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue don: and we not onely haue brought forth no good fruit, but rotten vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauory, to prouoke rhy Maieſtye withall: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all theſe our ſins, it would pleaſe thee in that loue, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall thou haſte firſte loued vs, when we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee, &amp; in that long patience wherein thou
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:180838:69"/>haſt hitherto born with vs, and doſt yet beare, &amp; tarrieſt for our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: to grant vs hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and earneſt repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, our heartes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing effectually touched with thy holye Spirite, ſtrikinge theſe rockye hearts of ours, that thei maye bee reſolued into riuers of teares for oure ſynnes, making them ſoft and meeke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the print of thy holy word, and ſeale of thy bleſſed ſpirite, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with thy fynger thine own laws in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo, that thou maiſt read
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:180838:70"/>thine owne hande, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thine owne ſeale, &amp; ſo paſſe by vs, when thou ſhalt bring thy iudgement vppon the face of the earth, for the iniquities thereof: whereof thou haſte gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſtill giueſt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time diuers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, which we beſeech thee may be profitable vnto vs, whilſte firſt of al we acknowledge thy hande ſtriking vs, and thy counſayle callinge vs thereby to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, that thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uier iudgementes doe not fall vpon vs, to our
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:180838:70"/>vtter deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, we thank thee (O Lorde) for that it hath pleaſed thee to be the watch-man, and as it were the ſpie of this Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, and haſte foreſeen al the ſtormes, and treaſons comming againſte it, and againſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hine annoynted oure SOVERAIGNE, whome thou in mercye haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to rule ouer it, and haſte ſcattered them and broughte them to naught, and haſte purſued certayne of thyne Ennemyes,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:180838:71"/>and ours vnto death, be ſeeching thee to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue this watchfull and carefull eye ouer vs, ſtill to doe vs good, and to purſue the reſt of thine enemies and ours vnto the graue: giuing not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto them, vnto whom thou haſte left place of repentaunce. And to this ende, raiſe vp the harts of our moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous QVEENE, &amp; her honourable Counſell thy Magiſtrates, that as they ſit in thy ſeate, and are called by thy name, ſo they maye execute
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:180838:71"/>thy iuſtice, which thou ſo well approoueſt of, whereof alſo thou wilt require a ſtraighte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt at their hands. Wee deſire thee alſo, to ſhewe theſe thy graces to all other Churches of thine, namely, thy Church of Englande, that it may enioye that peace that thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it: and graunt that the ſame be referred to that end wherfore thou haſt giuen it: namelye, to the ful eſtabliſhment of the throne of thy dear ſonn our Sauiour IESVS CHRIST, &amp;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:180838:72"/>to the building of his Kingdome there. Wee beſech thee alſo, for the churches which thi ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hath pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted long ſince, eſpeciallye thoſe, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue receiued knowledge in time of our ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, places of refuge in time of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution : that it woulde pleaſe thee to continue thy louing kindnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cauſe them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their faith toward thee, &amp; obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy holy worde. And whenſoeuer it ſhal bee thy pleaſure, to try
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:180838:72"/>them with any kinde of affliction , it woulde pleaſe thee to graunt vnto them , that they maye put their truſte in thee, hauing regarde to the truth of thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to the good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that they haue of thy helpe in tymes paſte, and thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue comfort &amp; hope, (O Lorde) euen of life in death, and of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in deſtruction. We praye thee alſo (good lord) that we may haue the feeling of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our brerhren, as members of the ſame
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:180838:73"/>body, &amp; thoſe that liue by the ſame ſpirite. And therefore we pray thee, that according to the manifold troubles that thou ſhalt viſite them with, it woulde be thy good pleaſure, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out thy grace in ſuch plentifull maner, that thy children maye patiently beare, &amp; ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye attende, for the good howre wherein thou wilt pul them out of all their troubles. And ſpecially we pray thy maieſty for our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that are afflicted for thy Goſpell ſake:
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:180838:73"/>namely, thoſe that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer impriſonment or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in any nation, for the clearer teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of it: that it woulde pleaſe thee to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patience in all theire troubles, wiſedom and mouthes to defend thy cauſe, againſt all thoſe that riſe vp againſte it: that thou woldſt bleſſe their trauels and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, for that for which they are taken: which is, to giue a freer courſe of thy goſpel into al pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces And therewithall wee beeſeeche thee for the churches of France
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:180838:74"/>and Flaunders, which are ſo miſerably racked and torn in ſunder, and which are almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with theſe fierie trials: that it wold pleſe thee to locke vpon the ſighings and gronings, the teares that fall from their eies continually, the bloud that is ſhed in all partes of the Lande, the bodies that lye vnburied, to bee meate to the foules of the ayre, and Fiſhes of the Sea, the lonenes of wiues lacking ther huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, children their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; euery frend his
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:180838:74"/>freind. And for aſmuch as thoſe thynges are come vppon them for thy names ſake, let it be thy good pleaſure to hepe them conſidering that they are forſaken of al their friends rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de about: and therefore praye thee that thou wouldeſt not looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our ſinnes, nor the ſins of our forefathers, wherby we deſerue not onelye this correction, but vtter deſtruction, as Sodom &amp; Gomorrha: but rather to look vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thi mercies which were before them: whereby
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:180838:75"/>thou haſt ſayde, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we do offende, and thou doeſt correct vs, yet thou wilt not take away thy mercyes from vs, but wilt leaue a remnant which thou wilt multiply, and make as the ſtarres of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and as the ſandes of the Sea. Looke alſo (O Lord) vpon the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſnes and cruelty, vnfaithfulnes, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of the enemies, wherewithall they blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thee, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke thee to thy face, and therefore in thine owne cauſe, and for
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:180838:75"/>thine own ſake, take the matter into thine owne handes, and pay vnto the Boſomes of thine enymies double and treble of that they haue giuen to thee. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt them, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to thine holy ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, haſten their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that afterward thy iudgement may haſten vpon the earth, and the inhabitants therof may learn to knowe thee by thy iudgementes; that would not vnderſtand and come to thee, by the louing callinge of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:180838:76"/>thy Goſpell. Wee pray thee (O Lorde) for our brethren that are vp in arms in both thoſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: that thou wouldſt goe before them, and come behinde them, and on euerye ſyde of them: couer their heads in the daye of battell, teache their handes to fyght, &amp; their fingers to war: giue them wiſdom &amp; valiantnes, and good ſucces in al their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes: ſtrike a dizineſſe &amp; maze of ſpirite into the enimies hearts, and take away from them al force, and diſappointall
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:180838:76"/>their counſels. And vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our brethren in Fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders wee beſeeche thee that thou wouldeſt comfort them ouer al their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and breaches that haue beene made in vpon them: &amp; where there are new forces e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day gathered, new ſleights inuented to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it maye pleaſe thee, to ſcatter their forces, and bring their ſleights to nothing. Yea grant alſo (O lord) that that whiche they haue deuiſed againſt thy chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, may come vppon
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:180838:77"/>their own heades. And for oure Brethren in Fraunce wee beſeeche thee (O Lorde) what ſtraights ſoeuer they be in, thou wouldeſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them: and althogh they be forſaken in the iudgement of all the world, and in their own iudgementes, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thou that haſt the iſſues of death in thine owne handes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer thoſe that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to death. And finally we moſt humbly thanke thee, for that it hath pleaſed thee to keepe vs this daye, and
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:180838:77"/>all the dayes and times of our liues, beſeeching thee, that thou wouldſt receiue vs this night in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy holye keeping, that we may haue quiet reſt, not of bodyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but of our ſoules alſo, reſtinge from all thoſe thinges that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to thy moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will, attending while thou raiſeſt vs vp in the morning, to do al thoſe thinges that thou haſte appoynted vs. Theſe thinges wee deſire of thee, &amp; all other things (which thou knoweſt to be more needfull for
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:180838:78"/>vs, &amp; thy whol church, better then we our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues do know) for Ieſus Chriſts ſake: ſaying the ſame praier, that he him ſelf hath taught vs. Our father. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A PRAYER FOR <hi>the Euening.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde God, Father euerlaſting and full of pitty, we acknowlege and confeſſe that we be not worthye to lift vp oure eyes to heauen, muche leſſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent oure ſelues before
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:180838:78"/>thy maieſty, with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that thou wilt heare our prayers and graunt our requeſtes, if we conſider our owne deſeruinges, for our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences do accuſe vs, &amp; our ſinnes do witnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, and we know that thou art an vpright Iudge, which doſt not iuſtifie the ſinners and wicked men, but punni ſheſt the falts of al ſuch as tranſgreſſe thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: yet moſt mercifull Father, ſince it hath pleaſed thee, to Commaunde vs to call vpon thee in all
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:180838:79"/>our troubles &amp; aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes promiſing euen then to helpe vs when we feel our ſelues (as it were) ſwallowed vp of death and deſperation. We vtterly renounce al worldlye confidence, &amp; flye to thy Soueraigne bounty, as our only ſtae and refuge: beſeeching thee not to call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſinnes and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes : whereby we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallye prouoke thy wrath and indignation againſt vs: neither our negligence and vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which haue neither
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:180838:79"/>worthely eſteemed, nor in our liues ſufficiently expreſſed the ſweet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of thy Goſpell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto vs: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to accept the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, &amp; death of thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, who by offering vp his body in ſacrifice once for all, hath made a ſufficient recompence for all our ſinnes. Haue mercye therefore vppon vs (O Lorde) and forgiue vs our offences. Teach vs by thy holye ſpirte, that we maye rightly weigh them, and earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent for the ſame. And
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:180838:80"/>ſo much the rather (O Lord) becauſe that the reprobate and ſuche as thou haſt forſaken can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not praiſe thee nor call vpon thy name: but the repenting hart, the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull mind, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience oppreſſed, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring and thirſting for thy grace, shall euer ſet foorth thy praiſe &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And albeit we be but wormes and duſte, yet thou art our Creator, &amp; we be the worke of thy hands: yea thou art our Father, and we thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: thou art our ſhe p-heard, and we thy flock:
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:180838:80"/>thou art our redeemer, and we thy people who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt bought: thou art our God, &amp; we thine inhertiance. Correct vs not therfore in thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger (O lord) neither ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to oure deſerts puniſh vs, but merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye chaſtice vs with a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affection, that all the worlde may know, that at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him of his ſinn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the botto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his hart, thou wilt put away his wickednes out of thy remembrance.</p>
               <p>Finally for as much as it hath pleaſed thee to
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:180838:81"/>make the night for man to reſte in, as thou haſte ordayned him the daye to trauaile, graunt O deare Father that wee may ſo take our bodely reſt, that our ſoules may continuallly watch for the time that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſhal appear for our deliuerance out of this mortall life, and in the mean ſeaſon that we not ouercome by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fantaſies, dreames or other temptations, may fully ſet our mindes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thee, loue thee, fear thee, &amp; reſt in thee. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore that our ſleep
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:180838:81"/>be not exceſſiue or ouer much after the vnſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſires of the fleſhe, but only ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent oure weake nature, that we may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpoſed in all godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy holy name, &amp; profite of our brethren. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A Prayer for all times.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, Father of mercy and God of al conſolation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whome wee haue
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:180838:82"/>neither hope nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, we pore wretches &amp; miſerable ſinners, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee of thy father<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly goodnes to look vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, and ſo make vs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of thy gratious goodnes, that we may ſtil increaſe in all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that euermore we may ſet forth thine honor &amp; glory: let our conuerſation bee ſuch, that a great mani behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding our good workes, may glorify thee oure heauenly father: &amp; ſo direct our ways, that we may hold forth the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy goſpel, as a
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:180838:82"/>lanthorn to lighten the ſteps of a greate many that they may turne to thee, &amp; praiſe thy name in their viſitation. Thus (O Lord) we beſeeche thee to deale with vs, that in deed we may be veſſels of honour vnto thee, now to ſet foorth the praiſe of thy name, and after this tranſitory life, to behold thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who haſte immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity alone, and dwelleſt in lighte, that no man hath approched vnto: remoue far from vs our ſinns &amp; iniquities, that they may not ſeperate
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:180838:83"/>betweene vs and thee: blot out all our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and make our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers righteous, that thou mayſt fauourably grant our requeſts: looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs with thy fauourable mercie, that thou mayſt haue pitty vpon vs, and beholde in the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of thy beloued Sonne Chriſt Ieſu, and that wee may bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented faultleſſe in thy ſight: and thou accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs as only, we may finde the Grace euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to ſet foorth thy honour and glory, and to ſpeake of thy prayſes
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:180838:83"/>in the middes of all thy people. Let vs loue (O Lord) the thinges that thee good, and hate the things that are euill: let vs delight in all things that may pleaſe thee, &amp; let vs bee greeued with whatſoeuer is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in thy ſight. And to the intent wee may haue true vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding and be able to diſcerne betweene things, what is good or euill, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee let thy word dwell plentifully in vs, which may guide oure vnderſtandings ſo, that we may abound in all
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:180838:84"/>knowledge, and do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which is righteous. And in this eſtate of the true Chriſtianity, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in minde, and ready in body to all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obedience, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche thee make vs to growe and encreaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace to grace, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth to fayth, vntill we come vnto the fulneſſe of age to be perfect members of the body of Chriſte, waiting for the bleſſed hope of thine elect, and ſighing in ſpirite vntill that thy children ſhalbe reuealed. In the meane
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:180838:84"/>ſeaſon, let vs ſigh with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al thoſe that haue recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the firſt fruits of thi ſpirit, that theſe days of ſinne may ceaſe, that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan be trode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der feet, that Antichriſt may be reuealed, yet to many thouſandes that be in ignoraunce, that the number of thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect may be full, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of thy ſaintes made perfect, all teares wiped from oure eyes, euen then when thy ſonne ſhal appear again the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time, to iudge the quicke and the deade, which time (O Lorde)
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:180838:85"/>ſend quickly, according to thy good will, and teache vs to pray with all thy Sayntes, Come Lord Ieſu, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: graunt this (O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) for thy Sonnes ſake, in whoſe name we pray vnto thee. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee bee but Earth and Aſhes, yet are we bolde to ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, (the GOD of all glory) euen as hee hath taught vs. Our Father whiche art in Heauen, hallowed bee thy name. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:180838:85"/>
               <head>A Prayer for the eſtate of the whole church.</head>
               <p>O Lorde our God &amp; heauenlye Father, foraſmuche as by thy holy word we are com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded in our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayers, not only to be mindfull of our ſelues, but alſo of al others thy children, yea, euen of our enimies: wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto thy Maieſty all thy whole true and Catholique Church, &amp; euery member thereof: that as it hath pleaſed
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:180838:86"/>thy goodneſſe by the bright beams of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly worde, to ſhine ouer the whol world, wherbi thou haſt expelled, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen away, &amp; cauſed to vaniſh, the dark &amp; miſty clouds of ignorance &amp; ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt voucheſafe by thy holy ſpirit to touch the hearts of men, that thei may ioyfullye embrace that, thine ſo high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſent amongeſt vs, that thorough our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes we prouoke not thy maieſty in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to take it from vs. Cruſh, bruſe, &amp; deſtroy
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:180838:86"/>with the breath of thy mouth, the mighty po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of that man of ſin, which ſo proudly exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him ſelfe aboue all that is called God. Let not thy ſimple flocke (deare father) in whoſe conſciences he of long time hath, and yet doth ſit as God, be any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger poiſoned with his ſweet enticing poiſons: but ſo lighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their harts that they may perceiue his iuglinges, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ſweet &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable doctrine of life euerlaſting, reuealed in thy glorious Goſpell.</p>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:180838:87"/>
               <p>And for aſmuch as it hath pleaſed thee in mercy aboue all natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the earth, to powre down the ſweet ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of thy Heauenlye Graces, vppon this our Engliſh nation aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantlie, in more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wiſe watering the ſame with the giftes of the holy ſpirite, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting thy Goſpell, &amp; ouerthrowing Idolatri, we beſech thee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue thy fauour toward the ſame, &amp; vtterly root out al remnants, reliques, &amp; Monumentes of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, that thy glorious
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:180838:87"/>name may be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye exalted, in ſincere, pure, and holy worſhip. And as thou haſte in mercy from amongſt vs in this thy Church, vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly baniſhed all falſe, venemous and poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doctrine, wherwith the ſoules of thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren heeretofore haue bene wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to death, and in place therof, haſt placed the true &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable doctrine of life euerlaſting, wherewith the ſoules of thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be fedde and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed to euerlaſtinge ioy: ſo in like mercy &amp;
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:180838:88"/>fauour we beſeech thee deere father, eſtabliſhe in the ſame thy church, a true, perfect, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere regiment thereof, according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript rule of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed worde, all fantaſies of mans brayne, and Dreames of humane policy vtterlye aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: that thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maieſtye onelye maye bee exalted in the light of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious goſpell: and that thy Churche flouriſhe and increaſe, beeing thorough thy protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ayded, ſupported,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:180838:88"/>maintayned and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: we beſeeche thee by thy holy Spirit, guid and rule euerye parte and member thereof, eſpecially thy ſeruaunt ELIZABETH our Queene, whome thy gratious fauoure and prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted a cheefe member in the ſame: vnder whoſe winges next vnto thy protection it hathe a cheefe ſuccour and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. Graunt vnto her, O LORDE, a pure and perfecte zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all thynges to promote thy Glorye:
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:180838:89"/>firſt and chiefly in labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and endeuoring of her ſelf earneſtly, in wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping away and purging out of thy Church all blots and deformityes, to reduce the ſame to a pure &amp; ſincere forme of worſhip, agreing to thy bleſſed word, vtterly to mooue all ſtumblinge blockes, which ſtay and hinder the courſe of thy goſpell: giue her in like maner O Lord, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of wiſdome, diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and gouernment, that with equitye and iuſtice ſhe maye ſee this whole Realme, which
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:180838:89"/>thou haſt committed to her charge, peaceablye and quietly gouerned: that ſhe may ſtudiouſly labour, that as wel tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the whole realm vertue be exalted, and vice abandoned: as ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in her own houſe and Court, that all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vanityes of this world, all licentious &amp; inordinate life, all flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and diſſimulation being vtterly baniſhed, the feare of thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maieſtye maye ſo raigne in the heartes of all within her pallace &amp; Court, that their liues
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:180838:90"/>and conuerſation may be agreable to thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wil, in ſincerity and true holines and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of life, that from them, as from the head, maye ſhine puretye of life and conuerſation, as an example and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of true Godlines to the whole Realme. Preſerue her, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee good Lord, from all conſpyracies and treaſons, that if it be thy good will, ſhee may haue a long &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et raigne ouer vs, to the benefit of thy Church, &amp; the aduancement of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:180838:90"/>thy glory. Indue the whol cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, good lord with the true &amp; perfect wiſdom, that in all their conſultatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels, hauing thee preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eies, thy mai conſult of thoſe things, which principally and cheefely may be for the aduauncement of thy glory, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity of thy church, and next for the quiet peace and gracious gouernmente of this realm. So lighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al inferior magiſtrats of this realm, good Lord, with the brightneſſe of thy holy Spirite, that
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:180838:91"/>vnderſtanding thy will, they may zealouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, maintain &amp; further the courſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell with the ſwoord of iuſtice, cut off the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, &amp; cheriſh the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Defend and gouern by the holye ſpirite, the Paſtours of thy church, &amp; labourers in thy vine yarde, that they maye zealouſly, earneſtly and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly feed thy flock committed vnto them, with the foode of lyfe thy bleſſed word, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with their ſoules maye bee nouriſhed to life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. Increaſe the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:180838:91"/>number of them, deare Father, place ouer eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye flocke a godly, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and painful Paſtor, who may painfully and carefully trauail, euery one in his charge, to bring thy people (which now alas in moſt partes doe wander and goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray like loſt ſheepe) to the true knowledge of thee their lord &amp; God, and of their deare Son Chriſte Ieſu their Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. And for thy mercy we beſeech thee, to take pity vpon thy poore &amp; and ſimple flocke, roote out al rauening wolues,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:180838:92"/>whiche haue craftilye crept into thy ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde and do make ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocke of the ſoules of thy ſimple flocke. Caſt out all hirelinges, time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruers, and dumbe Dogges, whiche to fill theire bellyes onelye, haue thruſt them ſelues among the ſheep, &amp; do pitifully ſuffer the flock of Chriſt thy ſonne, to bee deuoured and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered of the wolfe. Stir vp, good Lord, &amp; place in their rooms faithfull ſhepheards, which dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, paynfully, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and earneſtly may
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:180838:92"/>labour in thy vineyard, ſeek to win the ſouls of thy people, out of the tyranny and power of Satan, to the freedome of thy deere ſon Chriſt Ieſu our Lord.</p>
               <p>And that thy Church may be furniſhed with Godly learned paſtors, we beſeeche thee proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and encreaſe in all Godly knowledge, all Schooles of learning, eſpeciallye the two v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyuerſities, CAM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BRIDGE and OX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORD: grant deer father vnto all the ſtudents of the ſame, that the cheef
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:180838:93"/>end of all their ſtudyes maye be to the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of thy Church, and maintenance of the common wealth. Bleſſe their ſtudies, deare Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that all vaine ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſet a ſide, they may ſo fructify and profit in all profitable and godly ſciences, that heereafter they may become pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable members in thy Church, and godly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders of the common wealth.</p>
               <p>Graunt, good Lord, to all the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of this realm, that their hartes beeing tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:180838:93"/>with a ſincere fear and reuerence of thy heauenlye maieſtye, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in placing ouer them a godly Princeſſe, they may euery one in their callinges, walke in all true and humble obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto her, in thee &amp; for thee, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtaunce, tumultes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or rebellions: kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that to reſiſte the higher powers, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt thy maieſty. Finally we beſeech thy goodneſſe, ſo guid and gouerne the harts of all
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:180838:94"/>the whole realme of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery degree, that euery one in his calling, being by thy grace ſupported, may ſo occupy his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that thy glory in al thinges may be aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, thy Church enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, &amp; this whole realm into ſincere godlineſſe vertuouſly reduced.</p>
               <p>Moreouer we beſeech the (O Lord our God) in mercye beholde all thoſe which ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wordes ſake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, death, or baniſhment, or whatſoeuer els: ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:180838:94"/>then them good Lord, that they hauing thee alwais before their eies, and the glorye layde vp for them in the lyfe to come, may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaunt in defending thy truth, with out feare of man or vain allureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the world, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it come by lyfe or death, they may glorify thy holye name in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in the truth to the ende. Preſerue in like maner wee beſeech thee, all others thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whome it hath pleaſed thee with anye other kinde of Croſſe
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:180838:95"/>to chaſten for their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, whether by peſtilence, famine, war, pouerty, impriſonment, ſicknes or baniſhment, trouble of conſcience, vexation of ſpirite, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietnes of mind, want of ſpirituall comfort, or what ſoeuer kind of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of bodye or minds, thou doeſt try them with: that by thy holy ſpirite beeing fully aſſured, that thou by this thy correction min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt to call them backe to a feeling of their ſin, and due conſideration of their life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:180838:95"/>that they maye patiently abide thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly triall, looking for aide, helpe and comfort from thee, when it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth moſt conuenient to thy godly wiſdome: and beeing by thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull hande once deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, may acknowlege thy ſingular power and worke, giuing all laude and praiſe to thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, all the dayes of their life, ſtudye to liue before thee in ſincerity and perfect holineſſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to their liues ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:180838:96"/>
               <head>A PRAYER FOR <hi>all eſtates.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lorde God Father of light, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is no chaunge, neither yet ſhadow of chaunge, but haſte eſtabliſhed thine appoynted coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which ſhall not bee changed for euer: thou (O God) haſte made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs this diuerſitie of eſtates and degrees, according as euerye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth requyreth, keepe vs all, we beſeech thee, that we may walke obedientlye in our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:180838:96"/>and followe the ſteppes that thou haſte ſet before vs, euen from the higheſt to the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, let vs accompliſhe that duety vnto which thou haſt appointed vs, and with a faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made of old to our father ABRAHAM, that thou art his exceeding great rewarde, we maye likewyſe depend on thy prouidence, and ſeeke not any ſhameful waies to get our liuing, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dringe from the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of our voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, into the manifold
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:180838:97"/>errors of ſinne and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: looke vppon vs (O Lord) and inrich vs with thy grace, make vs obedient to our inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, meeke towardes our enemies, faithfull to our friendes, true &amp; iuſt towardes all men, that we may dwell ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rooted in the hope of thine elect, vntill thou ſhalt make an end of all our labors: looke vpon oure moſte Excellent Queene, and her hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Counſell, and as thou haſte called them to the higheſt roome, ſo giue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:180838:97"/>meaſures of grace, that they faithfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the talents com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them: lead them with the good King DAVID into thy ſanctuary, that they may ſee thy louing kindnes which is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life, and ſaye with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: All fleſh is graſſe, and the glory of man is as the flower of the field, and ſo conſecrate them ſelues to doe thy will, offer vp their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be holy, liuely &amp; reaſonable ſacrifices vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that they maye be Nurſes and nurſ-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:180838:98"/>vnto the Church: looke alſo wee beſeech thee vpon thy miniſters whome thou haſte ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of thy Goſpell, make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (O God) faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful diſpenſers of thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, without reſpect of perſons to doe the worke vnto the which thou haſte appointed them, that they maye conuert Sinners, and haue their glorye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the day of chriſt: and knitte vs togeather in peace and loue, that wee maye bee full of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion one towards
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:180838:98"/>an other, to reioyce with them that reioyce, and mourne with them that mourne, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to inſtruct one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the wayes of righteouſneſſe, that by our mutuall helpe wee maye the better with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande our enemye, and dwell, ſafe in hope of thine electe, till oure dayes ſhall be full, and wee ſhall walke the wayes of all the world, which time we beſeech thee bring vs happelye vnto, euen for thy Sons ſake wee beſeeche thee, to whome with thee
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:180838:99"/>and the holye Ghoſte, three perſons and one God, be all honour and glory now and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A PRAYER FOR <hi>the Queene.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Gratious Lorde, &amp; moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee acknowledge thee the Lord of lords, and the King of Kings, creating at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp; ruling al things euermore in heauen &amp; in earth, according to thy wonderfull wiſdom
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:180838:99"/>and power: and our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be thy poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, the worke of thy hands, &amp; the ſheepe of thy paſture, ſubiected to thy high maieſty, and depending vpon thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly prouidence for al thinges. Neuertheles, ſeeing thou in thy wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome annoynteſt kings and Queenes, appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to rule ouer thy people, to ſitte as Lieuetenauntes in thy ſeat, to miniſter iuſtice, and moſte of all, as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Nurſes to maintaine and cheriſhe thy Church: comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:180838:100"/>vs not onely to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and honour them, but moreouer to praie for them, as watching ouer vs for our good: wee therefore beſeeche thee for thy gret names ſake, and for IESVS CHRISTS ſake, to ſhew thy mercy to all Kinges and Princes, that mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy glorious goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: but eſpeciallye we praye thee to bleſſe our gratious Queene, in all ſpirituall bleſſinges in Chriſte Ieſus, and in all te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral bleſſings, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that in the great
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:180838:100"/>meaſures of thy effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al loue, ſhee may more and more find great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes of verttue, and wiſdom, and ſtrength in Chriſt Ieſus to the faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful &amp; happye diſcharge of her duty: that her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, &amp; ioy, and zeal of thy houſe may be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied and enerlaſting. And, ſeeing it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed thee of thy ſingular mercy, to giue her this eſpeciall honour, firſt to ſuffer for thy glorious truth, and afterwarde miraculouſli deliuering her out of the hands of all Her ennemyes, and
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:180838:101"/>to ſet vp a crowne vpon her heade, and to make her the inſtrumente to aduaunce thy glory and goſpell for which ſhee ſuffered, and to bring it out of darkneſſe into light, out of perſecution into this great and long peace: as we giue thee moſt harty thankes for this ſingular benefit, ſo we beſech thee to make her &amp; vs euermore tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k full for it, &amp; in thy good pleaſure ſtill to preſerue her, for the continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theſe bleſſinges to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, with all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:180838:101"/>to thy glory, the benefit of thy Church, and her infinite peace in Chriſt Ieſus, the Prince of peace. And furthermore we pray thee for her, &amp; the eſtate, that ſuch as be enemies of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and her enemies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, for the defence ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, may not deſpiſe the peace offered them to repentaunce, but that they maye account thy long ſuffering, and her peaceable &amp; vnbloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy gouernement an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſaluation to their ſoules, and vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned loue to the truth, &amp;
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:180838:102"/>their merciful ſouerain. Otherwiſe if they ſtill remaine diſobedient to the truth, diſobedient to her hihgneſſe, and dangerous to the ſtate, then (O God of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation) as thou haſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered them, ſo diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them ſtill, as thou haſt preuented them, ſo preuent them ſtill, and let their eies waxe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with looking, &amp; their harts faint with waiting for the comminge of that, which yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not, neither let it come (O Lorde) wee beſeeche thee, but a
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:180838:102"/>bleſſed, and a longe raigne to her, and peace to SION for euermore.</p>
               <p>Alſo (deare Father) ſo bleſſe, ſo loue, ſo in thy ſpirite ſanctify and keepe her, that ſhee maye in the ſpirite of counſel and fortitude, ſo rule that other Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter alſo, namelye, this her common wealth, that they maye flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe togeather, and growe vp togeather as Palme trees, in beautie, and in ſtrength, giuing ayde and helpe one to an other, that in the
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:180838:103"/>Church the glorye of God maye appeare, as the ſunne in his bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that the land may flow with milke &amp; hony, and true peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound therin, as in the tryumphant raigne of DEBORA.</p>
               <p>Theſe graces (O lord) are great, and we miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſinners, vnworthy of the leaſte of them: therfore looke not to vs but to thy ſelfe, not to oure iniquityes but to thy great mercies, accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting the death and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy ſonne, as a full ranſome for all our
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:180838:103"/>offences: throwing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the bottome of the ſea, &amp; making his croſſe and reſurrection effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall in vs to all obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and godlineſſe, as becommeth thy ſaints, that to all other thy good bleſſings towards our gratious ſoueraign, this may be added, that ſhe gouerneth bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, ouer a bleſſed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a people blaſſed of the Lorde, and beloued of the Lorde, and that thy graces may abound as the waters of the ſea, in the Prince and in the people, in the Church
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:180838:104"/>and in the Common wealth, from day to day till the day of our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation into the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where iuſtice inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, where we alſo ſhal inhabite and raign with thee, according to thy promiſe, for euer. Grant vs theſe things (O mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father) for thy deare ſonne our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe name we craue them at thy mercifull hande, praying further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more for them, as hee hath taught vs to pray. Our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:180838:104"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A PRAYER TO</hi> be ſayd in viſiting of the ſicke.</head>
               <p>O Our good GOD, Lord &amp; Father, the Creator and conſeruer of all thinges, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all goodnes &amp; benignitye, like as (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other thine infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite benefites, whiche thou of thy great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and grace doeſt diſtribute ordinarilye vnto all men (thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt them health of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to the end that they ſhould the better know
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:180838:105"/>thy great liberalitye, ſo that they might be the more readye to ſerue &amp; glorifye thee with the ſame: ſo contrarywiſe, when we haue ill beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued our ſelues in offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thy maieſtye, thou haſt accuſtomed to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhe vs, and call vs vnto thee by diuers and ſundry chaſtiſementes, thorough the which it hath pleaſed thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to ſubdue and tame our fraile fleſh, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye by thy grieuous plagues of ſickneſſe and diſeaſes, vſing the ſame, as a meane, to awake &amp;
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:180838:105"/>ſtir vp the great dulnes and negligence that is in vs all, and aduertiſing vs of oure euill life by ſuch infirmities &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, eſpecially when as they threaten the verye death, which (as aſſured meſſengers of the ſame) are all to the fleſh full of extreame anguiſhe and torments, althogh they be notwithſtanding to the ſpirit of the elect as medicines both good &amp; wholſom. For by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doſt mooue vs to retourne vnto thee for our ſaluation, and to cal vpon thee in our afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:180838:106"/>to haue thine helpe, which art oure dear and louing father. In conſideration wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee moſt earneſtlye praye vnto thee oure good God, that it wold pleaſe thine infinite goodnes to haue pitty on this thy poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture whome thou haſt, as it were, bounde and tied to the bed by moſt grieuous ſickneſſe, and brought to great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie by the heauineſſe of thine hand.</p>
               <p>O Lorde, enter not into a count with him, to render the rewarde
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:180838:106"/>due vnto his workes, but through thine infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercye remitte all his faults, for the which thou haſt chaſtiſed him ſo gently, and beholde rather the obedience which thy deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde hath rendred vnto thee, to witte, the ſacrifice which it hath pleaſed thee to accept as a full recompence for all the iniquities of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him for their iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice &amp; ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea for their onely ſauiour.</p>
               <p>Let it pleaſe thee, O GOD, to gyue him
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:180838:107"/>a true zeale and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to receiue and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him for his onely redeemer: to the end alſo, that thou maiſt receiue this ſicke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to thy mercy, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiyng all the troubles, which his ſins, the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of death, and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full feare of the ſame may bring to his weake conſcience: neither ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thou, O Lord, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the mighty ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary to preuaile, or to take from him the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which thou giueſt to thy dearely beloued
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:180838:107"/>children.</p>
               <p>And for as much as we are all ſubiect to the like ſtate &amp; condition, and to bee viſited with like battel, when it ſhal pleaſe thee to call vs vn to the ſame: we beſeech thee moſte humblye, O Lorde, with this thy poore Creature, whom thou now preſently cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtiſeſt, that thou wilt not extende thy rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous iudgement againſt him, but that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt vouchſafe to ſhew him thy mercye for the loue of thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:180838:108"/>who, hauing ſuffered the moſt ſhamefull, and extreame death of the Croſſe, bare willinglye the fault of this poore patient to the end that thou mighteſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, as one rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with his precious bloud, and receiued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the communion of his body, to be partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant of eternall felicity in the companye of thy bleſſed Aungels: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O Lord, diſpoſe, &amp; moue his hart to recieu by thy grace with all meekeneſſe this gentle and fatherly correction,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:180838:108"/>which thou haſte layde vpon him, that he maye indure it patientlye and with willing obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſubmitting himſelf with heart and minde to thy bleſſed will and fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mercye, wherein thou now viſiteſt him after this ſort for his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fit and ſaluation. It may pleaſe thy goodneſſe, O Lord, to aſſiſt him in all his anguiſhes and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. And although the tongue and voyce bee not able to execute their office in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half to ſet forth thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, that yet at the leaſt
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:180838:109"/>thou wilt ſtirre vp his hart to aſpire vnto thee only, which art the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye fountaine of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; thou wilt roote and ſettle in his hart the ſweet promiſes which thou haſt made vnto vs in Chriſte Ieſus thy ſonne our Sauiour, to the intent he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine conſtant againſt all the aſſaultes and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult, which the enemy of our ſaluation maye raiſe vp to trouble his conscience.</p>
               <p>And ſeeyng it hath pleaſed thee, that by the death of thy dear Son,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:180838:109"/>life eternall ſhoulde be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated vnto vs: and by the ſhedding of his bloud, the waſhing of our ſinnes ſhould be declared, and that by his reſurredio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, both iuſtice and immortality ſhoulde bee giuen vs, it may pleaſe thee to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this holy and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome medicine to this thy poore Creature in ſuch extremitie, taking from him all trembling &amp; dreadfull feare, &amp; to giue him a ſtout cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in the middes of all his preſent aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes.</p>
               <pb n="212" facs="tcp:180838:110"/>
               <p>And for as much as all thinges, O heauenly father, be knowne vnto thee, and thou canſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy good pleaſure, miniſter vnto him all ſuch thinges as ſhall be neceſſarye and expedient, let it pleaſe thee, O Lord, ſo to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him by thy grace, as may ſeeme moſt meete vnto thy diuine maieſty</p>
               <p>Receiue him, Lorde, into thy protection: for he hath his recourſe &amp; acceſſe to thee alone, &amp; make him conſtant and firme in thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and promiſes,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:180838:110"/>and alſo pardon all his ſinnes both ſecreat, and thoſe which are many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: by the which hee hath moſte grieuouſlye prouoked thy wrath &amp; ſeuere iudgementes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, ſo as in place of death (the whiche both he and al we haue iuſtlye merited) thou wilt graunt vnto him that bleſſed life, whiche we alſo attend &amp; looke for, by thy grace and mercy.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, O heauenlye Father, if thy good pleaſure bee that hee ſhall yet lyue
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:180838:111"/>longer in this worlde, it may then pleaſe thee to augment in him thy gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, ſo as the ſame maye ſerue vnto thy glorye: yea, Lord, to the intent he may conforme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the more diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and with more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, to the example of thy ſonne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: and that in renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him ſelfe he maye cleaue fullye vnto him, who, to gyue conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and hope vnto all ſinners, to obtaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of all their ſins and offences, hath car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed with him into the
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:180838:111"/>Heauens, the Theefe whiche was crucified with him vppon the croſſe.</p>
               <p>But if the tyme by thee appoynted bee come, that hee ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from vs vnto thee, make him to feele in his conſcience, O Lord, the fruite and ſtrength of thy grace, that thereby he may haue a new taſt of thy Fatherly care, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his lyfe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of the ſame, for the loue of thy dear ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:180838:112"/>
               <p>Giue him thy grace, that with a good heart, and full aſſuraunce of faith he maye receiue to his conſolation ſo great &amp; excellent a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to wit, the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his ſinnes in CHRIST IESVS thy Sonne, who now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth him to this pore perſonne in diſtreſſe, by the vertue of thy promiſes reuealed vnto him by thy woorde, which he hath exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with vs in thy Church and congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and alſo in vſing
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:180838:112"/>the ſacramentes, which thou haſt eſtabliſhed for confirmation of al their faith that truſte in thee vnfaynedly.</p>
               <p>Let true faith, O lord, be vnto him as a moſte ſure buckler thereby to auoyde the aſſaultes of death and more boldly walke for the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of eternall life, to the end that he hauing a moſt liuely apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion therof, may reioyce with thee in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens eternally.</p>
               <p>Let him be vnder thy protection and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, O heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:180838:113"/>and althogh he be ſick, yet canſt thou heale him: he is caſt downe, but thou canſt lift him vp: he is ſore troubled, but thou canſt ſende redres: he is weak, thou canſt ſende ſtrength: he acknowledgeth his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanes, his ſpots, his fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines &amp; iniquityes, but thou canſt waſh him, &amp; make him cleane: he is wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, but thou canſt miniſter moſte ſouerain ſalues: he is fearefull &amp; trembling, but thou canſt gyue him good courage and boldneſſe. To be ſhort, hee is, as it
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:180838:113"/>were vtterly loſt, and as a ſtrayed ſheepe, but thou canſte call him hoame to thee againe. Wherfore, O Lord, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this poore cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature (thine own work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip) reſigneth him wholly into thine ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, receiue him into thy merciful protection. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we poore miſerable creatures, which are, as it were, in the field rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fight til thou with draw vs from the ſame, vouchſafe ſo to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs by thine holye ſpirite, that we maye obtayne the victory in
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:180838:114"/>thy name, againſt oure deadly and mortal ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye. And furthermore, that the affliction and combat of this thy pore creature in moſte gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous tormentes, maye moue vs to humble our ſelues with all reuerent feare and trembling vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy mighty hande, knowing that we muſte appear before thy iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat, when it ſhal pleaſe thee to appoint. But O lord, the corupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our fraile nature is ſuch that wee are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlye deſtitute of anye mean to appeare before
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:180838:114"/>thee, except it peaſe the to make vs ſuch as thou thy ſelfe requireſt vs to be: &amp; further, that thou gyue vs the ſpirite of meekneſſe and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to reſt and ſtay who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye on thoſe thinges which thou only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeſt.</p>
               <p>But for as much as we be all togeather vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, to inioye ſuch benefites, wee beſeech thee to receiue vs in the name of thy deare Son our Lorde, &amp; maiſter, in whoſe death &amp; ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſtandeth wholly the hope of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="222" facs="tcp:180838:115"/>It may alſo pleaſe thee, O Father of comfort &amp; conſolation, to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then with thy grace, thoſe which imploye theire trauell and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to the ayding of this ſick perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they faint not by ouermuch and continuall labour, but rather to go hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cheerefully for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in doing their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours towards him: &amp; if thou take him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to comfort them ſo, as they may pacient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bear ſuch departing, and prayſe thy name in
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:180838:115"/>all things. Alſo, O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, vouchſafe to haue pition al other ſick perſons, and ſuch as bee by anye wayes or meanes afflicted, &amp; alſo on thoſe who as yet are ignorant of thy trueth, &amp; appertaine neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les vnto thy kingdom.</p>
               <p>In like manner on thoſe that ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, tormented in priſons, or otherwiſe troubled by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of thy veritye, for bearing Teſtimonye to the ſame: finally, on all the neceſſityes of thy people, and vpon al the
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:180838:116"/>ruins or decayes, which ſatan hath brought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy church. O father of mercy, ſpread forth thy goodnes vpon all thoſe that bee thine, that we forſaking oure ſelues, may be the more infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and confirmed to reſt onely vpon thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Graunt theſe our requeſtes, O our deare Father, for the loue of thy deare ſonne our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, who liueth &amp; raigneth with thee in vnity of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, true God, for euermore,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="225" facs="tcp:180838:116"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>PRAYERS AND</hi> thankeſgiuinges to be ſaid before and after meat.</head>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A Prayer before meate.</head>
                  <p>O Lorde our God and heauenly Father, in thy beloued ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, worke in our harts true repentaunce, with increaſe of a true and liuelye faith: make vs thankefull vnto thy Maieſtye for all thy benefites whiche wee continually do receiue at thy mercifull hande: Graunt vs the grace,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:180838:117"/>that we may at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with thankful harts as from thy handes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue meat and drincke for the ſuſtenaunce of our bodies, with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration vſe them to thy glory, and through thy bleſſing, receiue by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perfect nouriſhment: &amp; aboue all, wee craue at thy hands, good Lord, the heauenlye foode of our ſoules, which neuer periſheth: that through thy gratious goodnes, we maye be nouriſhed and ſtrengthened both in ſoule and body to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:180838:117"/>Chriſt our Sauiour. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A THANKESGIVING <hi>after meat.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ETernall God, and mercifull father, we yeelde vnto thee moſte harty thankes, for al thy benefites ſo plentifully beſtowed vppon vs: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially that thou haſt at this preſent, fed and nouriſhed oure mortall bodyes with meate and drinck: we beſeech thee in like manner let oure ſoules feele the ſweete
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:180838:118"/>taſte of thy heauenlye food, that we being fed and nouriſhed at thy handes, both in ſoule &amp; body, maye in this lyfe walke as it becommeth thy children, and in the life to come, be receiued to thine eternall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde and ſauiour. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A PRAYER <hi>BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meat.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O Mercifull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye Father, who giueſt food to euery li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:180838:118"/>creature, and with out whom nothing can liue, bleſſe and ſanctifie our meates &amp; drinckes, whiche wee are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to receiue, that they maye turne to the nouriſhment of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, wherevnto thou haſt appointed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that we acknowledging thy gratious goodnes in pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiding ſo liberallye for our bodyes, maye with cheerful harts be lifted vp earneſtly to long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the food of our ſouls wherby we may be fed eternally, through Ieſus Chriſt our ſauior. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="230" facs="tcp:180838:119"/>
                  <head>A THANKESGIVING <hi>after meate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O Heauenly Father, for theſe thy bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites wherewith thou haſte nowe ſufficiently fedde our bodies, wee beſeeche thee make vs thankful: &amp; as we feele the ſweetneſſe of them pleaſant to our bodies: ſo wee beſeeche thee, good Lorde, that the food of our ſoules, may be as pleaſant &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto our ſoules, &amp; that wee maye with as carefull hearts, prouide for the nouriſhment of
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:180838:119"/>our ſouls, as we are care ful for the nouriſhment of our bodies, till it ſhal ſhall pleaſe thy maieſty to bring vs to the place where wee ſhall neuer hunger nor thirſt more, but liue eternally, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Chriſte our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>A PRAYER BEFORE <hi>meate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O Lord our God and heauenlye Father, which haſte prouided meate and drinke for
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:180838:120"/>the nouriſhment of our bodies, giue vs grace to vſe them reuerentlye, as from thine handes with thankfull heartes. And as we doe greatlye hunger and thirſte for this foode of oure bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſo we beſeech thee good Lorde, that oure ſoules maye earneſtlye hunger after the lyke food and nouriſhment, that with earneſt minds wee maye ſeeke to haue our ſoules fed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed eternallye, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our onely Lorde and ſauiour Ieſus chriſt. So be it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="234" facs="tcp:180838:120"/>
                  <head>A THANKESGIVING <hi>after meate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>VVOnderful is thy prouidence, O Lorde, in preſeruing all liuing creatures. Grant vs grace we beſech thee that with thankful harts we maye acknowledge thy bountifull good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo liberally giuing vnto vs all things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: eſpecially feedingvs ſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with thy manyfold bleſſings, wherof agreat
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:180838:121"/>many of our brethren are deſtitute, as in like manner wee ſhould be, if thou didſt not deale more liberalitye with vs: graunt vs therefore, gratious Lord, that we maye bee thankfull for this thy goodneſſe, and to be mindful of them, which haue not ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance to releeue them: that beeing all members of one body, we may at length raign with our head Chriſte, to whom be al honour and glory, worlde with out end. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="235" facs="tcp:180838:121"/>
               <head>A GODLY PRAYER FOR <hi>the Morning.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">And may be ſung to the tune of the third Pſalme.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O God which art my part &amp; lot, my comfort &amp; my ſtay:</l>
                  <l>I haue decreed and promiſed, thy law to keepe alvvay.</l>
                  <l>Mine earneſt heart did humbly ſue, in preſence of thy face:</l>
                  <l>As thou therefore haſt promiſed,</l>
                  <l>Lord graunt me of thy grace,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My life I haue examined, and tride my ſecrete heart:</l>
                  <l>VVhich to thy ſtatutes cauſed me, my feete ſtraight to conuert.</l>
                  <l>I did not ſtay nor linger long, as they that flouthfull are:</l>
                  <l>But haſtily thy lawes to keepe,</l>
                  <l>I did my ſelffe prepare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The cruell handes of wicked men,</l>
                  <l>haue made of me their pray:</l>
                  <pb n="238" facs="tcp:180838:122"/>
                  <l>Yet vvoulde I not thy lavve forget, not from thee go aſtray.</l>
                  <l>Thy righteous iudgement ſhewde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward me, ſo great is and ſo high:</l>
                  <l>That euen at midnight will I riſe, thy name to magnifie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Companion am I to all them, vvhich feare thee in their hart:</l>
                  <l>And neither vvill for loue not dread, from thy commaundement ſtart.</l>
                  <l>Thy mercyes (lord) moſt plenteouſly, do all the world fulfill:</l>
                  <l>Oh teach me how I may obey, thy ſtatutes and thy vvill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All laud and prayſe be to the Lorde,</l>
                  <l>Oh that of might art moſt:</l>
                  <l>To God the father and the ſonne, and to the holy ghoſt.</l>
                  <l>As it in the beginning vvas, for euer heretofore:</l>
                  <l>And is novv at this preſent time,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall be euermore.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="235" facs="tcp:180838:122"/>
               <head>A GODLY PRAYER FOR <hi>the Euening.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">And may be ſung to the tune of the third Pſalme.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ACcording to thy promiſe Lord, ſo haſt thou with me dealt:</l>
                  <l>For of thy grace in ſundry ſorts, haue I thy ſeruant felt.</l>
                  <l>Teach me to iudge alvvaies aright, and giue me knovvledge ſure:</l>
                  <l>For certainly beleeue I do, that thy precepts are pure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet thou didſt touch me with thy rod I erred and vvent aſtray:</l>
                  <l>But I vvill keepe thy holy vvord, and make it all my ſtay.</l>
                  <l>Thou art both good and gratious, and giueſt moſt liberally:</l>
                  <l>Thy ordinauces hovv to keepe, therefore (O Lord) teach me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The proud and vvicked men haue forgde, againſt me many a lye:</l>
                  <l>Yet thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements ſtill obſerue, vvith all my hart vvill I.</l>
                  <pb n="238" facs="tcp:180838:123"/>
                  <l>Their hearts are ſvvoln vvith worldly vvealth, as greace ſo are they fat:</l>
                  <l>But in thy lavv do I delight, and nothing ſeek but that.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVho ſo vvith reuerence doth thee ſeare, to me let them retire:</l>
                  <l>And ſuch as do they couenats knevv and them alone deſire.</l>
                  <l>My heart vvithout all vvauering, let on thy lavves be bent:</l>
                  <l>That no confuſion come to me, vvherein I ſhould be ſhent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All laud and prayſe be to the Lorde,</l>
                  <l>Oh that of might art moſt:</l>
                  <l>To God the father and the ſonne, and to the holy ghoſt.</l>
                  <l>As it in the beginning vvas, for euer heretofore:</l>
                  <l>And is novv at this preſent time,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall be euermore.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:180838:123"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
